<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Operational Security Standard on Physical Security" documentID="12329" versionID="6" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="Preamble"><p>In accordance with the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578">Policy on Government Security</a> and <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16579&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix C of the Directive on Departmental Security Management</a>, this standard provides baseline physical security requirements to counter threats to government employees, assets and service delivery and to provide consistent safeguarding for the Government of Canada. The standard contains both requirements (indicated by use of the word “must” in sentences appearing in italics) and recommended safeguards (indicated by the use of the word “should”).</p><p>Baseline levels are designed for common types of threats that departments would encounter. Certain departments or operations may face different threats because of the nature of their operations, their location and/or the attractiveness of their assets. Examples include police or military establishments, health services, laboratories, sensitive research facilities, museums, service counters, offices in high-crime areas and overseas facilities.</p><p>The provisions pertaining to the storage, transmittal and destruction of classified and protected and other assets information apply to both government and non-government facilities.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="Definitions"><p>Refer to <a href="#appA">Appendix A</a> for definitions.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="3" title="Roles and Responsibilities"><p>All departments are responsible for safeguarding employees, assets and service delivery within their area of responsibility.</p><chapter anchor="3.1" title="Tenant Department Responsibilities"><p><a href="#Tenant">Tenant departments</a> are responsible for informing custodian departments of their security requirements for site selection and tenant fit-up. (See section 7 for further information.)</p></chapter><chapter anchor="3.2" title="Custodian Department Responsibilities"><p><a href="#Custodian">Custodian departments</a> are responsible for providing and funding safeguards considered necessary by the custodian to protect facilities, based on a threat and risk assessment conducted by or for the custodian. This responsibility includes implementing and integrating measures for <a href="#Base">base building security</a> (e.g., exterior doors and lighting), building systems (e.g., elevator, mechanical and electrical systems) and life safety (e.g., exit stairs, fire alarms and sprinklers). Custodians are also responsible for integrating tenant-funded requirements, both baseline and enhanced, into their base building infrastructure.</p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="4" title="Other Treasury Board Policies and Operational Security Standards"><p>This standard is complemented by other operational security standards found at the Treasury Board <a href="/sim-gsi/sp-ps/index-eng.asp">Security Policy</a> Web site and by technical documents on <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">physical security</a> produced by the RCMP.</p><p>The provisions of this standard complement the Treasury Board policies on <a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/RealProperty/siglist-eng.asp">real property<span class="wb-inv"> - Policies and Publications</span></a> and <a href="/hr-rh/osh-sst/index-eng.asp">occupational safety and health<span class="wb-inv"> - Policies and Publications</span></a>.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="5" title="Types of Threats Conditions"><p>The following threats are common to all government departments. Various events, accidental or intentional, can cause these threats to manifest themselves and produce injury.</p><chapter anchor="5.1" title="Work-related Violence"><p>Because of their duties or work-related situations to which they are exposed, employees are not immune from oral or written threats or acts of physical violence (e.g., assault as defined in the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-46/">Criminal Code</a>, intimidation and stalking) by other employees or members of the public. Work related threats can occur at the workplace or outside the workplace while employees are on duty or in some circumstances, off duty.</p><p>The Canada Labour Code recognizes the problem of violence and requires that employees be appropriately protected. The employer (the Government of Canada ) recognizes the need for employees to be free, to the greatest extent possible, of intimidation so that they can safely perform their mandated functions. The pending Violence Prevention Regulations set out the required method of response to internal and external acts of violence and the mandatory roles of the work place parties. <!--em-->The Regulations, once promulgated, must be followed when establishing procedures.<!--/em--></p><p>For further information refer to <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16579&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix C-Security Control Objectives</a> of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16579">Directive on Departmental Security Management</a>.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="5.2" title="Unauthorized Disclosure of Protected and Classified Information"><p>Unauthorized disclosure of protected or classified information can occur:</p><ol class="lower-alpha"><li>accidentally through loss or negligence by employees who were granted access to the information;</li><li>intentionally by individuals who have authorized (i.e., have been properly security screened and have a <a href="#Need">need to know</a>) access to the information; and
					</li><li>intentionally by individuals who gain unauthorized access to information by whatever means, e.g., targeting of protected and classified information by criminal, terrorist or foreign intelligence elements.</li></ol><p>The injury to the national interest or to private/non-national interests increases with the sensitivity of the disclosed information. Injury may include damage to the defence and maintenance of the economic, social or political stability of Canada, compromise of other governments' interests, breach of privacy, liability or financial loss, loss of confidence in the Government of Canada, or decrease of government efficiency. Unauthorized disclosure of Secret or Protected C information will create more injury than unauthorized disclosure of Protected A or B information. In addition, some classified or protected information may be more attractive than other information in the same security classification and may, therefore, require safeguarding above the baseline delineated for this level of information.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="5.3" title="Unavailability of Assets, and Monetary or Heritage Loss"><p>Theft, fraud, vandalism, cyber attack and “malicious activity”, accidental or intentional loss or damage by employees or members of the public, and natural events (such as power failure, fire or flood) are likely threats to <a href="#Assets">assets</a> that could deprive the government of their use, and disrupt program and service delivery. Another impact of these activities is the financial or heritage loss to Canadians in terms of replacement costs or the loss of items that are unique. The injury increases with the importance of the assets to Canadians and to the functioning of the federal government.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="5.4" title="Loss of Integrity"><p>Cyber attack and malicious activity, willful tampering and employee or system error can cause inaccuracy or loss of information, loss of authenticity and alter their intended use. The result is that Canadians could make wrong decisions and damage their economic or social circumstances. The impact also includes liability, financial loss, loss of confidence in government, and temporary or prolonged inability to govern properly. The injury increases with the importance of the information or other asset to Canadians and the government e.g., cheque producing equipment).</p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="6" title="Physical Security Approach"><p>The government's approach to physical security complements other aspects of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578">Policy on Government Security</a> (PGS) and is based on the theory that the external and internal environments of facilities can be designed and managed to create conditions that, together with specific physical security safeguards, will reduce the risk of violence to employees, protect against unauthorized access, detect attempted or actual unauthorized access and activate an effective response.</p><p>Physical security strategies are based on (1) the concept of protection, detection, response, and recovery; (2) design based on a series of clearly discernable zones; (3) control of access to restricted areas; and (4) the capability to increase security during emergencies and increased threat situations.</p><chapter anchor="6.1" title="Protection, Detection, Response and Recovery"><p><!--em-->Departments must ensure that their physical security strategy incorporates identifiable elements of protection, detection, response and recovery.<!--/em--></p><p>Protection is achieved through the use of physical, procedural and psychological barriers to delay or deter unauthorized access. Detection involves the use of appropriate devises, systems and procedures to signal that an attempted or actual unauthorized access has occurred. In the context of physical security response entails the implementation of measures to ensure that security incidents are reported to appropriate security officials and immediate and long-term corrective action taken in a timely fashion. <!--em-->Recovery refers to<!--/em--> the restoration of full levels of service delivery following an incident.</p><p><!--em-->Refer to<!--/em--><a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/g1-025-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-025, Protection, Detection and Response</a>, <!--em-->for more information.<!--/em--></p><p>With regards to recovery, refer to the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12324">Operational Security Standard - Business Continuity Planning Program</a>.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="6.2" title="Hierarchy of Zones"><p><!--em-->Departments must ensure that access to, and safeguards for, protected and classified <a href="#Assets">assets</a> are based on a clearly discernable hierarchy of zones. There are five zones:<!--/em--></p><dl><dt>Public Zone</dt><dd>is where the public has unimpeded access and generally surrounds or forms part of a government facility. Examples: the grounds surrounding a building, or public corridors and elevator lobbies in multiple occupancy buildings.</dd><dt>Reception Zone</dt><dd>is where the transition from a public zone to a restricted-access area is demarcated and controlled. It is typically located at the entry to the facility where initial contact between visitors and the department occurs; this can include such spaces as places where services are provided and information is exchanged. Access by visitors may be limited to specific times of the day or for specific reasons.</dd><dt>Operations Zone</dt><dd>is an area where access is limited to personnel who work there and to properly-escorted visitors; it must be indicated by a recognizable perimeter and monitored periodically. Examples: typical open office space, or typical electrical room.</dd><dt>Security Zone</dt><dd>is an area to which access is limited to authorized personnel and to authorized and properly-escorted visitors; it must be indicated by a recognizable perimeter and monitored continuously, i.e., 24 hours a day and 7 days a week. Example: an area where secret information is processed or stored.</dd><dt>High Security Zone</dt><dd>is an area to which access is limited to authorized, appropriately-screened personnel and authorized and properly-escorted visitors; it must be indicated by a perimeter built to the specifications recommended in the TRA, monitored continuously, i.e., 24 hours a day and 7 days a week and be an area to which details of access are recorded and audited. Example: an area where high-value assets are handled by selected personnel.</dd></dl><p>The last three zones, operations, security, and high security are referred to as restricted-access areas.</p><p>Instituting a hierarchy of zones allows departments to:</p><ol class="lower-alpha"><li>Store assets of different threat levels in the same facility,</li><li>Institute varied levels of controls of access to protect various levels in assets,</li><li>Reduce cost by processing and destroying various levels of information and assets within the same facility, and</li><li>With appropriate planning, change zones from one period of time (working hours) (eg. Operations zone) to another period of time (silent hours) (eg. Security zone).</li></ol><p>Access to the zones should be based on the concept of “<a href="#Need">need to know</a>” and restricting access to protect employees and valuable assets. Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/g1-026-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-026, Guide to the Application of Physical Security Zones</a> for more detailed information.</p><p>The appropriate number of zones within a facility is dependent on the number of tenants (single or multi-tenant) and the building owner / custodian (federal, provincial or municipal government or private sector). In a multi-tenant government building, the building security committee (see section 7.7.6.) should determine the hierarchy of zones for the common areas. The tenant is responsible for determining appropriate zones within its space.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="6.3" title="Control of Access"><p><!--em-->Departments must control access to <a href="#Restricted">restricted-access</a> areas using safeguards that will grant access only to authorized personnel<!--/em-->.</p><p><!--em-->Control of access to restricted-access areas and other departmental space must be provided in a manner which does not contravene the life safety requirements of the National Building Code of Canada, National Fire Code of Canada and related codes, standards and guidelines administered by the<!--/em--> Federal Fire Protection Association (<!--em-->FFPA<!--/em-->). Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-010 - Security Connotations of the 1995 National Building Code</a>, for more information on typical National Building Code security related issues.</p><p>Balancing effective <a href="#Control">control of access</a> for unauthorized persons and material while providing convenient access for authorized persons and materials is a challenge for any department. Areas of concern include pedestrian entrances, visitor screening, shipping and receiving areas, parking, utility spaces, mailrooms and corridors leading to <a href="#Restricted">restricted zones</a>.</p><p>Factors affecting the means of controlling access include such things as the size and location of the facility and the nature of activities undertaken there. For example, the requirement to control access might involve either a series of administrative procedures such as having visitors sign in and out, and having employees show identification badges to security personnel, or a system whereby visitors must contact an employee who would come and escort them into the facility. Facilities with few employees might consider personal recognition techniques to determine authorized and unauthorized individuals entering their space. Departments may also consider electronic access control (e.g., card access, PIN access or biometric access control) to meet the requirement for mandatory control of access. A threat and risk assessment will determine the appropriate cost effective means to control access to a facility.</p><p><!--em-->To facilitate the proper <a href="#Control">control of access</a> to departmental space, departments must carefully plan, using the TRA methodology, how individuals and material will enter their space.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->Departments must have appropriate procedures in place for screening incoming mail/deliveries for suspicious packages.<!--/em--> The nature and extent of such screening should be determined by a threat and risk assessment</p><p>For more detailed information see the <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/g1-024-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-024 Control of Access.</a></p></chapter><chapter anchor="6.4" title="Capability to Increase Security in Emergency and Increased Threat Situations"><p><!--em-->Safeguards for controlling access of personnel or protocols for managing the risk related to materials must incorporate the need to implement heightened levels of readiness during emergency and heightened-threat situations.<!--/em--> For more information refer to the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12331">Operational Security Standard - Readiness Levels for Federal Government Facilities</a>.</p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="7" title="Security in the Selection and Design of Facilities"><chapter anchor="7.1" title="Introduction"><p><!--em-->Departments must review their existing facilities as part of their threat and risk assessment activity to determine whether remedial measures are needed.<!--/em--></p><p>The requirements of this operational standard are neither specific to a particular type of facility nor all-encompassing. While they are typical of office buildings, they apply to other facility types (such as warehouses, laboratories, lands, bridges, wharves and dams) that may require unique safeguards to provide adequate security against the threats identified in this standard.</p><p>The <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578">Policy on Government Security</a> and <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16579&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix C-Security Control Objective</a> of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16579">Directive on Departmental Security Management</a> require departments to ensure that security is fully integrated early in the process of planning, selecting, designing and modifying their facilities. It is important to ensure that security is thoroughly addressed in all phases of a construction or modification project. A multidisciplinary team composed of security officials, occupational health and safety officials, real property experts and program and project managers should determine the appropriate security criteria for each project based on baseline security requirements and a threat and risk assessment. <!--em-->Departments must include the necessary security specifications in all plans, request for proposals and tender documentation for construction or modification projects and incorporate related costs in funding requirements.<!--/em--></p><p>The following information is intended for use by project managers and real property and security professionals in establishing a safeguarding strategy for a particular project.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.2" title="General Security and Planning"><chapter anchor="7.2.1" title="Applicable Codes and Policies"><p><!--em-->Departments must ensure that physical security measures comply with applicable regulations, codes and policies.<!--/em--> Examples include labour, fire, building and electrical regulations and codes and Treasury Board <a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/RealProperty/siglist-eng.asp">real property</a> policies.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.2.2" title="Emergency Power"><p><!--em-->Emergency power must be provided for base building services (e.g., partial elevator service and emergency lighting) to the extent appropriate for departmental facilities in order to facilitate safe evacuation in the event of an emergency and to protect government assets. A threat and risk assessment will determine the emergency power requirements for security systems (e.g., electronic door locks, CCTV, alarms). As a minimum, the emergency power must be provided in conformance with the National Building Code of Canada and the National Fire Code of Canada.<!--/em--></p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3" title="Perimeter Security - Considerations for Site Selection"><chapter anchor="7.3.1" title="Easements through Site and Emergency Lanes"><p>During site selection and lease negotiation, the possibility of any easements within or adjacent to the facility that could affect the security of personnel or <a href="#Assets">assets</a> should be examined. Easements that permit access to a site by utility crews, the public or emergency personnel limit the tenant's ability to control access; this may result in unauthorized people gaining access to the tenant's facility, employees or equipment.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3.2" title="Control of Site Perimeter"><p>Control of the site perimeter should be achieved through the application of crime prevention through environmental design principles. Examples include keeping intruders under observation through natural surveillance, decreasing crime opportunities through natural access control and creating a sense of ownership through territorial reinforcement as well as such landscape features as fences, planters and site grading.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3.3" title="Site Overview, Building Location and Topography"><p>The design, layout and site location of buildings should facilitate natural surveillance by police and the public from the surrounding area (e.g., from nearby roadways or other buildings) unless this approach is deemed undesirable by departmental safeguarding strategies. <!--em-->Departments must also refer to FFPA with respect to the suitability of the facility in the event of an emergency evacuation.<!--/em--></p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3.4" title="Emergency Services"><p>Fire water capacity and the effective response times of firefighters and police should be taken into account during the development of safeguarding strategies (based on protection, detection and response) that apply to site selection, facilities and assets. For example, alternative measures for life safety and asset protection may be required to compensate for inadequate emergency response times. <!--em-->Departments must seek and follow the direction of the FFPA with respect to the water supply requirements for fire fighting.<!--/em--></p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3.5" title="Adjacent Occupants and Use"><p>Consideration should be given to adjacent occupants and use during site selection, including the potential impact of adjacent occupants on the safety of departmental employees and on service delivery. Consideration should also be given to the impact of departmental operations on adjacent occupants (whether governmental or non-governmental).</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3.6" title="Illumination of Site"><p>Lighting should provide sufficient illumination in and around facilities to allow the detection and observation of people approaching the facility, discourage opportunistic criminal activity, address any other security threats that may apply (e.g., vandalism and work-related violence) and support surveillance features (e.g., natural surveillance and closed-circuit video systems). The choice of light levels should be based on applicable codes, camera technology and other security considerations. Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-002 - Security Lighting</a> for more information.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3.7" title="Exterior Signs"><p><!--em-->Where signs identify facilities occupied by federal government departments and agencies they must comply with the <a href="/fip-pcim/index-eng.asp">Federal Identity Program</a><!--/em-->. In addition, facilities should display signs that give clear directions for parking, visitors, employees and service areas. Consideration should be given to the conditions imposed by provincial or territorial law to prove trespass when signs are used to define the boundaries of government property or establish restricted-access areas in accordance with a TRA.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3.8" title="Landscape Design"><p>Landscaping should support protection of the building, detection of intruders, and response to security incidents. Landscape security features include:</p><ul><li>clearly marked boundaries;</li><li>circulation routes designed to promote natural surveillance;</li><li>no cover for intruders;</li><li>unobstructed views for security personnel, employees and the public of potential problem areas (e.g., where criminal activities might occur); and</li><li>avoidance of materials and furniture that might expose the facility to increased risk during a heightened state of security (e.g., if a demonstration turns violent).</li></ul><p>Landscape design should apply the principle of crime prevention through environmental design principles. Examples include keeping intruders under observation through natural surveillance, decreasing crime opportunities through natural access control and creating a sense of ownership through territorial reinforcement as well as such landscape features as fences, planters and site grading.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.3.9" title="Parking"><p>The threat and risk assessment will determine the needed safeguards to protect employees in parking areas. Such safeguards may include putting a designated parking area close to the facility, adequate lighting, or a buddy system whereby employees can be accompanied to their vehicles.</p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="7.4" title="Entry Security"><chapter anchor="7.4.1" title="Pedestrian Entrances and Entrance Lobbies"><p>One way of physically controlling access to a facility or its <a href="#Restricted">restricted access areas</a> is through the use of entry points. An entry point channels traffic at the facility (including employees and visitors) in a way that permits effective monitoring, screening or control by personnel, guards or automated means.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.4.2" title="Service and Utility Entry and Exit Points"><p><!--em-->Service and utility entrance and exit points (such as air intakes, mechanical ducts, roof hatches and water supplies) must be safeguarded to ensure that the facility's critical assets and life safety measures as well as departmental programs are not compromised by unauthorized or uncontrolled access.<!--/em--></p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.4.3" title="Shipping and Receiving Areas, Loading Docks and Mail Rooms"><p>Where possible, shipping and receiving areas, loading docks and mail rooms should not be directly linked or adjacent to restricted-access areas or critical facility infrastructure (such as water mains, cooling and heating systems, fire detection and alarm systems, electrical, telephone and data lines, and other service connections).</p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="7.5" title="Interior Security - Planning"><chapter anchor="7.5.1" title="Circulation Routes, Internal Circulation Corridors and Elevator Lobbies"><p><!--em-->Circulation routes which provide employees and visitors access to restricted-access areas must be carefully planned to ensure life safety requirements are met as well as to ensure that access is controlled to areas where valuable, protected and classified assets are stored.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->Planning the location of and activities related to protected and classified information and assets must ensure that the required safeguards are not compromised during emergencies.<!--/em--> For example having a High Security zone located on a particular floor such as a cross-over floor in a high rise building could require in the event of an emergency that public pass through the High security zone to gain access to a second stairwell. Other areas which require a balance between life safety and physical security concerns include elevator lobbies, corridors, and hardware limitations. <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/g1-024-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-024 - Control of Access</a>, <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/g1-024-fra.htm#AppA">Appendix A</a> provides Best Practices related to zoning and building layout, compartmentalization, cross over floors, access to exits etc.</p><p>Access by employees and visitors to restricted-access areas should be based on the principle of need to know with consideration of overviewing and overhearing.</p><p>The circulation routes followed by employees to transport valuable assets should be planned in a way that addresses the threats identified through a TRA including those identified in Section 5.</p><p><!--em-->Where applicable, access to tenant space from elevator lobbies must be controlled in respect of employees, contractors, visitors and service personnel.<!--/em--> Safeguards vary, depending on the nature of departmental programs, the size of tenant space and the number of people requiring access to a floor. They might include a physical barrier (such as a wall), an arrangement using personnel, a reception function, or procedures such as limiting elevator use to authorized personnel or having employees challenge people.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.5.2" title="Daycare Centres"><p><!--em-->When daycare centres are planned for federal facilities, consideration must be given to the safety of both the tenants and the public in the context of the Government of Canada's responsibilities and liability.<!--/em--> Daycare centres should not be co-located with departments whose programs or operations may be subject to interruption or increased threats due to events such as demonstrations, or with departments that might deal with high-risk clients (including potentially violent individuals).</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.5.3" title="Stairwells and Elevators"><p>Stairwells and elevators should not provide direct access to the tenant's restricted-access areas or to the custodian's critical facility infrastructure. Where possible, passenger and freight elevators (including those from parking and loading dock areas) should open into a Public or Reception Zone, such as the ground floor elevator lobby. However, elevators may open into tenant space, and exit stairwells may allow entry to the space, if such access is monitored continuously by the tenant, or if the space is secure at all times.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.5.4" title="Washrooms"><p><!--em-->Employee safety (as per Section 5.1) must be considered in regard to the location of employee and public washrooms<!--/em-->. When recommended by a TRA, employee washrooms should not be accessible from public or reception zones.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.5.5" title="Amenity Spaces"><p><!--em-->Consideration must be given to employee safety during the design and layout of common amenity spaces (such as gymnasiums, food service areas, common meeting rooms or conference facilities).<!--/em--> It should not be necessary for personnel to enter a department's restricted zone in order to access a common amenity space.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.5.6" title="Telecommunications Wiring Within a Facility"><p>A TRA should be used to determine appropriate physical security measures for telecommunications wiring within a facility. Additional information can be found in the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15746">Treasury Board's Information Technology Standard 6.9: Canadian Open Systems Application Criteria (COSAC), Telecommunications wiring system in Government-Owned and leased buildings - Implementation Criteria</a>.</p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="7.6" title="Controlling Restricted-Access Areas"><p>Departments have several choices available to control access to restricted-access areas: personal recognition, access badges, mechanical measures, electronic control of access, etc. The appropriate choice will depend on the location of building, number of employees, threat and risk assessment etc. Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/g1-024-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-024 Control of Access</a>, for more information on methods to Control access.</p><chapter anchor="7.6.1" title="Identification Cards"><p><!--em-->All government employees <strong>must be</strong> issued an identification (ID) card, which as a minimum includes the name of the department, the bearer's name and photo, a unique card number and an expiry date<!--/em-->. A signature is recommended. Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/g1-006-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-006 Identification cards/Access badges</a>, for more information</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.6.2" title="Access Badges"><p>Access badges indicate authorized employees and visitors<!--em-->. Where personal recognition or escorts are not feasible, a temporary access badge must be issued to all visitors (including non authorized employees, contractors, service personnel)<!--/em--> which clearly identifies them as a non employee. Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/g1-006-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-006 Identification cards/Access badges</a>, for more information.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.6.3" title="Electronic Access Control"><p>An electronic access control is a safeguard that will assist in controlling access to a facility. A threat and risk assessment will assist in determining the need and cost effectiveness of such a system. Sometimes when a department chooses to implement an electronic access control system, the requirements for an ID card and an access badge are combined in one electronic access control card.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.6.4" title="Closed Circuit Video Equipment (CCVE)"><p>Closed circuit video surveillance/assessment equipment may assist a department in providing appropriate monitoring of access to their facility. A threat and risk assessment will assist in determining the need for CCVE.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.6.5" title="Security Control Centre"><p>A security control centre, whether proprietary or off site, is a focal point for monitoring the various systems such as an electronic access control system, an electronic intrusion detection system and closed circuit video equipment. This centre will typically include other personal or life safety equipment such as the fire alarm panel. A control centre of this nature would typically only be used in the larger facilities.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.6.6" title="Sensitive discussion areas"><p>A sensitive discussion area (SDA) is an area that is specially designed and managed to prevent the overhearing of Protected and Classified information at various levels of sound attenuation. Owing to the cost of building and operating an SDA, departments should carefully assess the need, the risk and cost-effectiveness of options. When construction and use of an SDA is being considered, the RCMP should be consulted on needs definition, options, construction standards and procedures for the proper administration of the SDA.</p><p>For further information, see the <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-004 - Construction of a Special Discussion Area</a>.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.6.7" title="Secure rooms"><p>Secure rooms are rooms constructed according to technical standards for the storage of Protected and Classified information and assets.</p><p>Classified and Protected information stored in the appropriate type of secure room need not be further protected by storage in additional security containers, unless the application of the need-to-access principle is still a concern. A records office where protected and classified information is stored on open shelves must be constructed as a secure room. For further information see the <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-029 - Secure Rooms</a> for construction specifications for SR-1 (low security) and SR-2 (high security) respectively.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.6.8" title="Security Guards"><p>If a TRA identifies a security requirement that necessitates a human function, then employing guards in that situation is appropriate. In this case various issues related to guard type (proprietary or contract), duties, training, equipment and safety, should be addressed. For additional recommendations regarding guard services, refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-008 - Guidelines for Guard Services</a>.</p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="7.7" title="Facility Management"><chapter anchor="7.7.1" title="Leases and Other Occupancy Agreements"><p><!--em-->Physical security requirements for facilities must be included in any leases and other occupancy agreements.<!--/em--></p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.7.2" title="Cleaning and Maintenance Services"><p>Where cleaning or maintenance is required during limited access hours the custodian should be the contract authority.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.7.3" title="Interior Signs"><p>There should be at least one prominent sign inside the main entrance to facilities that directs visitors to the Reception Zones of federal tenants.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.7.4" title="Locking Hardware and Key Control"><p>Commercial grade hardware should be used for all locks. In addition, a complete keying protocol should be organized for the facility. The locks on perimeter doors should be keyed separately from other locks, and they should not enable access with a master key.</p><p><!--em-->Keys for the entire facility, spare keys and the information needed to reproduce keys must not all be stored in the same container.<!--/em--> Master keys should not leave the building. Security and High Security Zones should not be part of the master keying system.</p><p>Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guides G1-016, G1-017 and G1-018</a> for more information on Hardware, Doors and Frames, and Master Key Systems respectively.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.7.5" title="Renovation Work"><p>Where renovation work needs to be done within restricted zones, there should be advance consultation between the security and real property officials of custodian and tenant departments on security arrangements for access by contractor personnel.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="7.7.6" title="Facility Security Committee"><p>In multi-tenant facilities, a security committee chaired by major tenant or the custodian should be organized to coordinate the custodian's and tenants' requirements for control of access and to plan safeguards for heightened security situations. The tenant representatives should be authorized by their departmental security officers to make planning decisions for security measures such as guard services.</p></chapter></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="8" title="Storage"><chapter anchor="8.1" title="General"><p><!--em-->Protected and classified information must be stored in approved containers and restricted-access areas as per the minimum requirements laid out in Appendix B.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->Protected and classified assets, (e.g., classified research and development equipment, engineering models or prototypes) must be stored in containers approved for that purpose as listed in the <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-001 - Security Equipment Guide</a>.<!--/em--> For requirements not met by items listed in the Security Equipment Guide, contact the RCMP Technical Security Branch.</p><p>Care needs to be taken to ensure that classified and protected information and valuable assets (e.g., laptops) are properly safeguarded when occupants are away from their workstations for any length of time.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="8.2" title="Security Containers"><p>When different levels of protected or classified assets are stored together, storage should comply with the standard set for the most sensitive asset involved. The infrequent storage of a relatively small amount of assets having high-level sensitivity with a larger amount of assets with a low-level sensitivity may not warrant enhanced safeguards; refer to Appendix B.</p><p>Classified information should not be stored with valuable assets such as cash or drugs in the same <a href="#Security">security container</a>.</p><p>Brief cases are not considered storage containers and should not to be used as such. Refer to Section 9 <!--em-->Transport and Transmittal.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->Departments must develop procedures for the storage of assets shared with the Government of Canada, other Canadian governments, foreign governments, international, educational and private sector organizations. Procedures must be in accordance with agreements or arrangements between the parties concerned and the GSP.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->All employees working off site must safeguard information as per the minimum requirements outlined in Appendix B.<!--/em--> Employees should also consult the TB <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12559">Policy on Telework</a>. With respect to off-site contract work, departments should use the <a href="/tbsf-fsct/350-103-eng.asp">Security Requirements Checklist</a> (TBS/SCT 350-103) to define the contract requirements for safeguarding protected or classified assets at the contractor's facilities.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="8.3" title="Valuable Assets"><p><!--em-->Valuable assets must be afforded protection against loss, destruction or alteration.<!--/em--> The degree of protection afforded is dependant on the asset itself and the TRA. Some protection measures are contained in the <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-001 - Security Equipment Guide</a>. Additional information can be obtained by contacting the RCMP's Technical Security Branch.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="8.4" title="Keys for Security containers"><p>Keys in this section include mechanical keys, combinations, personal identification numbers, and access cards.</p><p><!--em-->Keys for <a href="#Security">security containers</a> must be safeguarded commensurate with the highest sensitivity of the information or asset to which the key provides access. This requirement also applies to records that would allow the reproduction of a key.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->Keys that provide access to security containers must be changed when (1) there is evidence of compromise, (2) a threat and risk assessment indicates an unacceptable level of risk, or (3) an employee's need to access the security container has changed. Combinations to security containers should be changed every year.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->A record of all changes to keys for security containers must be kept, including: the date, reason, custodian, location and, if applicable, lock identifier, combination number, duplicates, etc. This record of change must be secured commensurate with the highest security level of the information/asset being protected within the container.<!--/em--></p></chapter><chapter anchor="8.5" title="Disposal or Recycling of Security Containers"><p>Departments are responsible for the disposal of security containers. <!--em-->Approved security containers for Protected C and classified information must not be disposed of or resold to private sector or outside agencies.<!--/em--> Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-001 - Security Equipment Guide</a> for more information.</p><p>The department is responsible for ensuring that prior to disposal or recycling, all containers are stored in an operations zone as a minimum, all contents have been removed and record logs have been amended accordingly.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="8.6" title="Service and Maintenance of Security Containers"><p><!--em-->Departments must ensure that approved storage equipment is properly serviced and maintained at all times.<!--/em--> Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-001 - Security Equipment Guide</a> and related News/Bulletins for more information.</p></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="9" title="Transport and Transmittal"><p>Maintaining authorized access to protected and classified assets and valuables is paramount when being transported.</p><ol><li><!--em-->When transporting protected and classified assets from one person or place to another, safeguards must include controlling access to the information by need-to-know.<!--/em--> This also applies to the servicing of containers.</li><li><!--em-->When transmitting protected and classified assets from one person or place to another, safeguards must depend on proper packaging, an appropriate and reliable postal or courier service (government or private sector) and the anonymity of the information while in transit.<!--/em--></li><li>For the limited amount of protected and classified assets that are at higher risk, appropriate additional safeguards should be used, as indicated in the TRA.</li><li><!--em-->Departments must transport or transmit protected and classified assets according to the minimum requirements set out in Appendix C.<!--/em--></li><li>Refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-009 - Transport and Transmittal of Sensitive Information and Assets</a> for detailed specifications for enveloping, addressing and courier services for transporting and transmitting protected and classified assets.
				</li><li>Departments are responsible for safeguarding security equipment (for example, security containers) during transport for servicing requirements.</li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="10" title="Destruction"><chapter anchor="10.1" title="Storage of Protected and Classified Waste"><p><!--em-->Protected and classified assets awaiting destruction (either on- or off-site) must be stored at minimum in approved <a href="#Security">security containers</a> or appropriate secure room as per Appendix B. Departments must safeguard information in transit to destruction, in the manner prescribed for the highest level of classified or protected information involved (refer to <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-009 - Transport and Transmittal of Sensitive Information and Assets</a>).<!--/em--></p></chapter><chapter anchor="10.2" title="Destruction of Assets"><p><!--em-->Departments must establish procedures that will ensure security for the protection of protected and classified assets and valuables awaiting destruction. These procedures include:<!--/em--></p><ul><li>informing staff of the highest levels of protected and classified information that can be destroyed by the equipment within the office;</li><li>ensuring that authorized personnel are present to monitor the destruction of protected and classified assets and/valuables; and</li><li>segregating protected and classified information awaiting destruction away from non-sensitive information.</li></ul><p><!--em-->Protected and classified information with no historical or archival value for which the retention period have expired, must be promptly destroyed including surplus copies, draft copies and waste.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->Protected and classified information must be destroyed using equipment listed in the <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-001 - Security Equipment Guide</a>.<!--/em--> For requirements not met by items listed in the Security Equipment Guide, contact the RCMP Technical Security Branch.</p><p><!--em-->When a department is responsible, on behalf of another department, for transporting protected and classified information to destruction, or for destroying such information, written authorization of destruction must be obtained.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->Protected and classified information must not be disposed of through a federal or municipal recycling program unless properly destroyed in an approved manner prior to recycling.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->The destruction of information must be performed by individuals in the department who are appropriately security screened to the highest level of protected or classified information being destroyed.<!--/em--></p><p><!--em-->Departments must ensure that anyone who performs shredding is security screened commensurate with the highest level of information being destroyed.<!--/em--> Departments are also responsible for ensuring that the shredded material conforms to the size standards noted in <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-001 - Security Equipment Guide</a>.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="10.3" title="Electronic Storage Media"><p>For guidance on the disposal and destruction of electronic storage media see the Communications Security Establishment Canada (CSEC) <a href="https://www.cse-cst.gc.ca/en/node/270/html/10572">Information Technology Security Guideline (ITSG-06) - Clearing and Declassifying Electronic Data Storage Devices</a>.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="10.4" title="Emergency Destruction Abroad"><p><!--em-->In situations abroad where the likelihood of emergency destruction is high, there must be local orders for the prompt destruction of Top Secret and Secret information when its secure transport or transmittal to Canada is not feasible.<!--/em--> These orders should be reviewed periodically and kept in a location known to authorize personnel for access during an emergency. Orders should specify that:</p><ul><li>all destruction equipment is properly maintained;</li><li>sufficient numbers of authorized personnel know how to use the equipment; and</li><li>priority lists for destruction are updated regularly and are available.</li></ul></chapter></chapter><chapter anchor="11" title="Enquiries"><p>Enquiries about this policy should be directed to the Departmental Security Officer. For interpretation of the standard, the Departmental Security Officer should contact the <a href="/cioscripts/cu-cn/contact-eng.asp?who=/sim-gsi/">Security and Identity Management Division</a>.</p></chapter></chapters><appendices><appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A - Definitions"><p>For the purposes of this standard the following definitions apply.</p><dl><dt id="Assets">assets <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(biens)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>Tangible or intangible things of the Government of Canada. Assets include but are not limited to information in all forms and media, networks, systems, materiel, real property, financial resources, employee trust, public confidence and international reputation.</dd><dt>attack <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(attaque)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>any action to execute a threat.</dd><dt>availability(<!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">disponibilité)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>the condition of being usable on demand to support operations, programs and services.</dd><dt id="Base">base building security <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(sécurité de l'immeuble de base)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>Security safeguards provided by the custodian department to protect a facility but not the assets contained in the building. Basic building security provides a base or starting point for other security requirements (i.e. minimum and enhanced safeguards) to be added to protect the specific assets held by the institution.</dd><dt>baseline security requirements <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(exigences de base)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>mandatory provisions of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578">Policy on Government Security</a> and its associated operational standards and technical documentation.</dd><dt>business continuity planning <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(planification de la continuité des activités)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>an all-encompassing term which includes the development and timely execution of plans, measures, procedures and arrangements to ensure minimal or no interruption to the availability of critical services and assets.</dd><dt>classified assets <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(biens classifiés)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>assets whose compromise would reasonably be expected to cause injury to the national interest.</dd><dt>classified information <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(renseignements classifiés)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>information related to the national interest that may qualify for an exemption or exclusion under the Access to Information Act or Privacy Act, and the compromise of which would reasonably be expected to cause injury to the national interest.</dd><dt>compromise <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(compromission)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>unauthorized disclosure, destruction, removal, modification, interruption or use of assets.</dd><dt id="Control">control of access <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(contrôle de l'accès)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>Ensuring authorized access to assets within a facility or restricted areas by screening visitors and material at entry points by personnel, guards or automated means and, where required, monitoring their movement within the facility or restricted access areas by escorting them.</dd><dt id="Custodian">custodian department <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(ministère gardien)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>a department having administration of federal real property.</dd><dt>department <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(ministère)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>as described in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578&amp;section=text#cha2">Section 2: Application</a>, of the PGS. In this document the term “department” may refer to either the tenant, the custodian or both.</dd><dt>destruction equipment <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(équipement de destruction)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>any device or process used to change the medium which contains classified or protected information in such a way that the classified or protected information can no longer be derived from the medium.</dd><dt>detection <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(détection)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>the use of appropriate devices, systems and procedures to signal that an attempted or actual unauthorized access has occurred.</dd><dt>facility <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(installation)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>a physical setting used to serve a specific purpose. A facility may be part of a building, a whole building, or a building plus its site; or it may be a construction that is not a building. The term encompasses both the physical object and its use (for example, weapons ranges, agriculture fields).</dd><dt>information <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(renseignements)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>any pattern of symbols or sounds to which meaning may be assigned.</dd><dt>integrity <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(intégrité)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>the accuracy and completeness of assets, and the authenticity of transactions.</dd><dt>material <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(matériel)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>any tangible object with the exclusion of those embodying information.</dd><dt>monitored <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(surveillé)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>To watch for or detect a breach of security.</dd><dt>monitored continously <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(surveillée continuellement)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>To confirm on a continuous basis that there has not been a breach of security. Examples include electronic intrusion detection system, or someone guarding a particular point on a constant basis.</dd><dt>monitored periodically <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(surveillée sur une base périodique)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>To confirm on a regular basis that there has not been a breach of security. The frequency and diligence of monitoring is based on the recommendations of a Threat and Risk Assessment. Examples include a guard patrol, or employees working at the location.</dd><dt>national interest <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(intérêt national)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>Concerns the defence and maintenance of the social, political and economic stability of Canada.</dd><dt id="Need">need-to-know <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(besoin de connaître)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>The need for someone to access and know information in order to perform his or her duties.</dd><dt>personnel security screening <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(enquêtes de sécurité du personnel)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>the process of examining the trustworthiness and suitability of employees and, where national interest is concerned, their loyalty and associated reliability. When satisfactory, an employee is granted reliability status or a security clearance. Reliability status applies when only protected assets are concerned. When the employee has access to classified assets, a security clearance corresponding to the level of classified assets is issued. A security clearance includes reliability status. See Screening.</dd><dt>physical security <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(sécurité matérielle)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>the use of physical safeguards to prevent or delay unauthorized access to assets, to detect attempted and actual unauthorized access and to activate appropriate responses.</dd><dt>protection <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(protection)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>for physical security, protection means the use of physical, procedural and psychological barriers to delay or deter unauthorized access, including visual and acoustic barriers.</dd><dt>protected information <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(renseignements protégés)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>information related to other than the national interest that may qualify for an exemption or exclusion under the Access to Information Act or Privacy Act, and the compromise of which would reasonably be expected to cause injury to a non-national interest.</dd><dt>protected and classified information <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(renseignements protégés et classifiés)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>See Protected Information and Classified Information.</dd><dt>recovery <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(rétablissement)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>to the restoration of full levels of service delivery.</dd><dt>response <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(intervention)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>the implementation of measures to ensure that security incidents are reported to appropriate security officials and immediate and long-term corrective action taken.</dd><dt id="Restricted">restricted - access area <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(zone d'accès restreint)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>work areas where access is limited to authorized individuals includes Operations, Security and High Security Zones. Refer to the definition in Section 6.3. Hierarchy of Zones.</dd><dt>risk <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(risque)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>the chance of a vulnerability being exploited.</dd><dt id="Security">security container <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(coffre de sécurité)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>any totally enclosed storage place for a classified asset, designed to resist force and surreptitious attacks; e.g., a safe, security cabinet, strongbox, permanent vault, demountable vault or secure room.</dd><dt>screening <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(triage)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>the process of verifying visitors and/or material (e.g. incoming mail/deliveries) at entry points of a facility or a restricted area for authorizing access; See Personnel Security Screening.</dd><dt>shredding <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(déchiquetage)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>a mechanical cutting or grinding method of reducing standard weighs of office paper, microfilm and microfiche to fragments.</dd><dt>surreptitious attack <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(attaque subreptice)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>a secret unauthorized attack to breach or circumvent a defensive system or some of its components in such a manner that the custodians and/or security force cannot readily detect the attack.</dd><dt id="Tenant">tenant department <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(ministère locataire)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>a department occupying federal real property that is under the administration of another department or Crown Corporation.</dd><dt>threat <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(menace</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>Any potential event or act, deliberate or accidental, that could cause injury to employees or assets.</dd><dt>unauthorized access <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(accès non autorisé)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>Access to assets by an individual who is not properly security screened and/or does not have a need-to-know.</dd><dt>unauthorized disclosure <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(divulgation non autorisée)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>Disclosure that is forbidden by law or by governmental or departmental policies.</dd><dt>value <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(valeur)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>estimated worth: monetary, cultural or other.</dd><dt>vulnerability <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(vulnérabilité)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>an inadequacy related to security that could permit a threat to cause injury.</dd><dt>zones <!--em--><span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(zones)</span><!--/em--></dt><dd>A series of clearly discernible spaces to progressively control access</dd></dl></appendix><appendix anchor="B" title="Appendix B - Minimum Safeguards for Protected and Classified Assets"><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><tr class="active"><th id="Tbl1_H1"><strong>Activities</strong></th><th id="Tbl1_H2" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Protected A</strong></th><th id="Tbl1_H3" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Protected B</strong></th><th id="Tbl1_H4" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Protected C</strong></th><th id="Tbl1_H5" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Confidential</strong></th><th id="Tbl1_H6" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Secret</strong></th><th id="Tbl1_H7" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Top Secret</strong></th></tr><tr><th id="Tbl1_H8" headers="Tbl1_H1"><strong>Personnel Security Screening</strong></th><td colspan="6" headers="Tbl1_H8 Tbl1_H2 Tbl1_H3 Tbl1_H4 Tbl1_H5 Tbl1_H6 Tbl1_H7"><strong>Refer to Personnel Security Screening Standard</strong></td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl1_H10" headers="Tbl1_H8"><strong>Storage</strong></th><td headers="Tbl1_H10 Tbl1_H8 Tbl1_H2">Operations Zone: Lock up the information</td><td headers="Tbl1_H10 Tbl1_H8 Tbl1_H3">Operations Zone: Lock up the information or if recommended by a TRA, select appropriate equipment from RCMP Guide G1-001, Security Equipment Guide</td><td headers="Tbl1_H10 Tbl1_H8 Tbl1_H4">Security Zone: Select appropriate container from RCMP Guide G1-001, Security Equipment Guide</td><td headers="Tbl1_H10 Tbl1_H8 Tbl1_H5">Operations Zone: Select appropriate container from RCMP Guide G1-001, Security Equipment Guide</td><td colspan="2" headers="Tbl1_H10 Tbl1_H8 Tbl1_H6 Tbl1_H7">Security Zone: Select appropriate container from RCMP Guide G1-001, Security Equipment Guide</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl1_H11" headers="Tbl1_H1"><strong>Mailing in Canada</strong></th><td colspan="6" headers="Tbl1_H8 Tbl1_H2 Tbl1_H3 Tbl1_H4 Tbl1_H5 Tbl1_H6 Tbl1_H7"><strong>Refer to Appendix C and RCMP Guide G1-009, Standard for the Transport and Transmittal of Sensitive Information and Assets</strong></td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl1_H13" headers="Tbl1_H11"><strong>Paper Destruction</strong></th><td headers="Tbl1_H13 Tbl1_H11 Tbl1_H2">Commercially available paper shredder producing a strip-cut to a maximum width of 3/8" (10mm) or transfer to National Archives for Destruction.</td><td headers="Tbl1_H13 Tbl1_H11 Tbl1_H3">Commercially available paper shredder producing a strip-cut to a maximum width of 3/8" (10mm) or if recommended by a TRA, select appropriate equipment from G1-001 or transfer to National Archives for Destruction</td><td colspan="4" headers="Tbl1_H13 Tbl1_H11 Tbl1_H4 Tbl1_H5 Tbl1_H6 Tbl1_H7">Select appropriate equipment from RCMP Guide G1-001, Security Equipment Guide, or transfer to National Archives for Destruction</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl1_H14" headers="Tbl1_H11"><strong>Facsimile Transmission</strong></th><td colspan="2" headers="Tbl1_H14 Tbl1_H11 Tbl1_H2 Tbl1_H3">Ensure receiving fax machine is within an operations zone.</td><td headers="Tbl1_H14 Tbl1_H11 Tbl1_H4">Ensure receiving fax machine is within a Security Zone, both devices are secure faxes and zone users and occupants have the same need-to-know as the recipient or the recipient is present to receive.</td><td headers="Tbl1_H14 Tbl1_H11 Tbl1_H5">Ensure receiving fax machine is within an Operations Zone, and both devices are secure faxes.</td><td colspan="2" headers="Tbl1_H14 Tbl1_H11 Tbl1_H6 Tbl1_H7">Ensure receiving fax machine is within a Security Zone, both devices are secure faxes and zone users and occupants have the same need-to-know as the recipient or the recipient is present to receive.</td></tr></table></appendix><appendix anchor="C" title="Appendix C - Minimum Safeguards for the Transport and Transmittal of Protected and Classified Assets"><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><thead><tr class="active"><th id="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Activities</strong></th><th id="Tbl2_H2" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Protected A</strong></th><th id="Tbl2_H3" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Protected B</strong></th><th id="Tbl2_H4" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Protected C</strong></th><th id="Tbl2_H5" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Confidential</strong></th><th id="Tbl2_H6" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Secret</strong></th><th id="Tbl2_H7" class="col-xs-2deldel"><strong>Top Secret</strong></th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="7"><section class="wb-fnote"><h2 id="table2-fn" class="wb-inv">Table 2 Notes</h2><dl><dt>Table 2 Note 1</dt><dd id="table2-fn1"><p>Single sealed envelope: A briefcase or other container of equal or greater strength, locked or sealed, can replace a single sealed envelope.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table2-fn1a-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 2 note </span>1<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Table 2 Note 2</dt><dd id="table2-fn2"><p>Reliable Courier Service: The reliability of a courier service must be established through verification with other clients, or the Better Business Bureau, or the local police.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table2-fn2a-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 2 note </span>2<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Table 2 Note 3</dt><dd id="table2-fn3"><p>SIARN: Sensitive Information and Assets Receipt Notification.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table2-fn3a-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 2 note </span>3<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Table 2 Note 4</dt><dd id="table2-fn4"><p>Approved Tape: Refer to PWGSC Security Equipment Catalogue or <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-001 - Security Equipment Guide</a>, to obtain information on the approved security tape.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table2-fn4-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 2 note </span>4<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Table 2 Note 5</dt><dd id="table2-fn5"><p>Appropriately Screened Service: Personnel of the service are security screened to a level commensurate with the information or assets they control. See <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-009 - Transport and Transmittal of Sensitive Information</a> and Assets, for mailing procedures if personnel are not appropriately screened.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table2-fn5a-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 2 note </span>5<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Table 2 Note 6</dt><dd id="table2-fn6"><p>Double Sealed Envelope: When proprietary mail or messenger service is used, the outer envelope can be replaced by a briefcase or other container of equal or greater strength, locked or sealed. Additional measures may also apply such as when involving bulk shipment. See <a href="http://www.rcmp-grc.gc.ca/physec-secmat/pubs/index-eng.htm">RCMP Guide G1-009 - Transport and Transmittal of Sensitive Information</a> and Assets.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table2-fn6a-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 2 note </span>6<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd></dl></section></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><th id="Tbl2_H8" headers="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Transport in Canada within restricted access area</strong></th><td headers="Tbl2_H8 Tbl2_H2 Tbl2_H3" colspan="2">Transport Discretely</td><td headers="Tbl2_H8 Tbl2_H4"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1a-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings</td><td headers="Tbl2_H8 Tbl2_H5 Tbl2_H6" colspan="2">Transport Discretely</td><td headers="Tbl2_H8 Tbl2_H7"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1b-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl2_H9" headers="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Transport in Canada Outside restricted access area</strong></th><td headers="Tbl2_H9 Tbl2_H2 Tbl2_H3" colspan="2"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1c-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed</td><td headers="Tbl2_H9 Tbl2_H4"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1d-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with security markings enclosed in a second secure enclosure (eg. locked brief case).</td><td headers="Tbl2_H9 Tbl2_H5 Tbl2_H6" colspan="2"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1e-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed</td><td headers="Tbl2_H9 Tbl2_H7"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1f-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with security markings enclosed in a second secure enclosure (eg. locked brief case)</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl2_H10" headers="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Transport outside Canada<br />
						within restricted access area</strong></th><td headers="Tbl2_H10 Tbl2_H2 Tbl2_H3" colspan="2">Transport Discretely. Envelope not required</td><td headers="Tbl2_H10 Tbl2_H4 Tbl2_H5 Tbl2_H6 Tbl2_H7" colspan="4"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1g-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl2_H11" headers="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Transport outside Canada Outside restricted access area</strong></th><td headers="Tbl2_H11 Tbl2_H2 Tbl2_H3" colspan="2"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1h-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed</td><td headers="Tbl2_H11 Tbl2_H4"><!--em-->Double sealed envelope.<!--/em--> Security mark the inner envelope and appropriately address</td><td headers="Tbl2_H11 Tbl2_H5"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1i-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed</td><td headers="Tbl2_H11 Tbl2_H6 Tbl2_H7" colspan="2"><!--em-->Double sealed envelope.<!--/em--> Security mark the inner envelope and appropriately address</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl2_H12" headers="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Transmit in Canada within restricted access area</strong></th><td headers="Tbl2_H12 Tbl2_H2 Tbl2_H3 Tbl2_H4 Tbl2_H5 Tbl2_H6 Tbl2_H7" colspan="6">Proprietary mail, messenger service or Departmental employee in a <!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1j-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl2_H13" headers="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Transmit in Canada outside restricted access area</strong></th><td headers="Tbl2_H13 Tbl2_H2 Tbl2_H3" colspan="2">Proprietary mail, messenger service, Departmental employee or communication letter mail (formerly first class mail) packaged in a <!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1k-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed, or a <!--em-->Reliable Courier Service<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn2a-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>2</a></sup> or similar postal service with record of transit and delivery, packaged as for communication letter mail. Use this method only if delivery is urgent.</td><td headers="Tbl2_H13 Tbl2_H4">Proprietary mail, messenger service, or Departmental employee in a <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6a-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with inner package security marked and appropriately addressed, or registered mail, in a <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6b-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with inner package security marked and appropriately addressed, or a <!--em-->Reliable Courier Service<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn2b-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>2</a></sup> or similar postal service <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6c-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with inner package security marked and appropriately addressed with record of transit and delivery, packaged as for registered mail. Use this method only if delivery is urgent.</td><td headers="Tbl2_H13 Tbl2_H5 Tbl2_H6" colspan="2">Proprietary mail, messenger service, Departmental employee or communication letter mail (formerly first class mail) packaged in a <!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1l-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed, or a <!--em-->Reliable Courier Service<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn2c-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>2</a></sup> or similar postal service with record of transit and delivery, packaged as for communication letter mail. Use this method only if delivery is urgent.</td><td headers="Tbl2_H13 Tbl2_H7">Proprietary mail, messenger service, or Departmental employee in a <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6d-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with inner package security marked and appropriately addressed, or registered mail, in a <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6e-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with inner package security marked and appropriately addressed, or a <!--em-->Reliable Courier Service<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn2d-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>2</a></sup> or similar postal service <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6f-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with inner package security marked and appropriately addressed with record of transit and delivery, packaged as for registered mail. Use this method only if delivery is urgent.</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl2_H14" headers="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Transmit outside Canada within restricted access area</strong></th><td headers="Tbl2_H14 Tbl2_H2">In a <!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1m-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed.</td><td headers="Tbl2_H14 Tbl2_H3 Tbl2_H4 Tbl2_H5 Tbl2_H6 Tbl2_H7" colspan="5">Proprietary mail, messenger service, or Departmental employee in a <!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1n-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed</td></tr><tr><th id="Tbl2_H15" headers="Tbl2_H1"><strong>Transmit outside Canada outside restricted access area</strong></th><td headers="Tbl2_H15 Tbl2_H2 Tbl2_H3" colspan="2"><!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1o-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed and transmitted by, Proprietary mail, messenger service, or Departmental employee or communications letter mail, or a <!--em-->Reliable Courier Service<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn2z-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>2</a></sup> or similar postal service with record of transit and delivery, packaged as for registered mail. Use this method only if delivery is urgent.</td><td headers="Tbl2_H15 Tbl2_H4"><!--em-->Appropriately Screened<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn5a-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn5"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>5</a></sup> proprietary mail, messenger service <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6g-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with a <!--em-->SIARN<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn3a-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn3"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>3</a></sup> placed in the inner envelope. Security mark the inner envelope and seal with <!--em-->approved tape,<!--/em--> or DFAIT mail service <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6h-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with a <!--em-->SAIRN<!--/em--> placed in the inner envelope. Security mark the inner envelope and seal with <!--em-->approved tape.<!--/em--></td><td headers="Tbl2_H15 Tbl2_H5"><!--em-->Appropriately Screened<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn5b-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn5"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>5</a></sup> proprietary mail, messenger service packaged in a <!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1p-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed, or a <!--em-->Reliable Courier Service<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn2x-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>2</a></sup> or similar postal service with record of transit and delivery, packaged in a <!--em-->Single sealed envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn1q-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>1</a></sup> with no security markings appropriately addressed, or DFAIT mail service <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6i-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with inner package security marked and appropriately addressed.</td><td headers="Tbl2_H15 Tbl2_H6 Tbl2_H7" colspan="2"><!--em-->Appropriately Screened<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn5c-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn5"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>5</a></sup> proprietary mail, messenger service <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6j-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with a <!--em-->SIARN<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn3b-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn3"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>3</a></sup> placed in the inner envelope. Security mark the inner envelope and seal with <!--em-->Approved Tape<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn4-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn4"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>4</a></sup>, or DFAIT mail service <!--em-->Double Sealed Envelope<!--/em--><sup id="table2-fn6k-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table2-fn6"><span class="wb-inv">table 2 note </span>6</a></sup> with a <!--em-->SAIRN<!--/em--> placed in the inner envelope. Security mark the inner envelope and seal with <!--em-->approved tape.<!--/em--></td></tr></tbody></table></appendix></appendices><!--footnotes>
		<footnote anchor="fn1" reference="fn1-rf" title="1" tooltip="Return to footnote 1 referrer">
			&#160;    
		</footnote>
		
		<footnote anchor="fn2" reference="fn2-rf" title="2" tooltip="Return to footnote 2 referrer">
			&#160;        
		</footnote>
		
		<footnote anchor="fn1" reference="fn1-rf" title="3" tooltip="Return to footnote 1 referrer">
			&#160;    
		</footnote>
		
		<footnote anchor="fn2" reference="fn2-rf" title="4" tooltip="Return to footnote 2 referrer">
			&#160;        
		</footnote>
		
		<footnote anchor="fn1" reference="fn1-rf" title="5" tooltip="Return to footnote 1 referrer">
			&#160;    
		</footnote>
		
		<footnote anchor="fn2" reference="fn2-rf" title="6" tooltip="Return to footnote 2 referrer">
			&#160;        
		</footnote>
	</footnotes--></doc>