<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Policy on Government Security" documentID="16578" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PolicyInstrumentSchema.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="1. Effective date"><p>1.1 This policy takes effect on July 1, 2009.</p><p>1.2 This version of the policy incorporates updates effective April 1, 2012.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="2. Application"><p>2.1 This policy applies to:</p><ul><li>All departments within the meaning of Schedules I, I.1, II, IV and V of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/f-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a> (<abbr title="Financial Administration Act">FAA</abbr>), unless excluded by specific acts, regulations or Orders in Council.</li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="3" title="3. Context"><p>3.1 Government security is the assurance that information, assets and services are protected against compromise and individuals 
are protected against workplace violence. The extent to which government can ensure its own security directly affects its 
ability to ensure the continued delivery of services that contribute to the health, safety, economic well-being and security 
of Canadians.</p><p>3.2 Security begins by establishing trust in interactions between government and Canadians and within government. In 
its interactions with the public when required, the government has a need to determine the identity of the individuals or 
institutions. Within government, there is a need to ensure that those having access to government information, assets and 
services are trustworthy, reliable and loyal. Consequently, a broad scope of government activities, ranging from safeguarding 
information and assets to delivering services, benefits and entitlements to responding to incidents and emergencies, rely 
upon this trust.</p><p>3.3 In a department, the management of security requires the continuous assessment of risks and the implementation, monitoring 
and maintenance of appropriate internal management controls involving prevention (mitigation), detection, response and recovery. 
The management of security intersects with other management functions including access to information, privacy, risk management, 
emergency and business continuity management, human resources, occupational health and safety, real property, materiel management, 
information management, information technology (<abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr>) and finance. Security is achieved when it is supported by senior management—an 
integral component of strategic and operational planning—and embedded into departmental frameworks, culture, day-to-day 
operations and employee behaviours.</p><p>3.4 At a government-wide level, security threats, risks and incidents must be proactively managed to help protect the 
government's critical assets, information and services, as well as national security. Advice, guidance and services provided 
by lead security agencies support departments and government in maintaining acceptable levels of security while achieving 
strategic goals and service delivery imperatives.</p><p>3.5 The management of security is most effective when it is systematically woven into the business, programs and culture 
of a department and the public service as a whole.</p><p>3.6 Deputy heads are accountable for the effective implementation and governance of security and identity management 
within their departments and share responsibility for the security of government as a whole. This comprises the security 
of departmental personnel, including those working in or for offices of Ministers or Ministers of State, and departmental 
information, facilities and other assets.</p><p>3.7 Ministers of the Crown, ministers, and Ministers of State are responsible for the security of their staff and offices 
as well as the security of sensitive information and assets in their custody, as directed by the prime minister.</p><p>3.8 This policy is issued under section 7 of the <abbr title="Financial Administration Act">FAA</abbr>.</p><p>3.9 Treasury Board has delegated to the President of the Treasury Board the authority to amend directives that support 
the policy in the following subject areas:</p><ul><li>Departmental security management</li><li>Identity management</li></ul><p>and to issue and amend standards that support the policy in the following subject areas:</p><ul><li>Information and identity assurance</li><li>Individual security screening</li><li>Physical security</li><li><abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> Security</li><li>Emergency and business continuity management</li><li>Security in contracting</li></ul><p>3.10 This policy is to be read in conjunction with the <em>Foundation Framework for 
Treasury Board Policies</em>, the <em>Directive on Departmental Security Management</em> and the <em>Directive on Identity 
Management</em>.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="4" title="4. Definitions"><p>4.1 For definitions of terms used in this policy, refer to <a href="#appA">Appendix A—Definitions</a>.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="5" title="5. Policy statement"><p>5.1 The objectives of this policy are to ensure that deputy heads effectively manage security 
activities within departments and contribute to effective government-wide security management.</p><p>5.2 The expected results of this policy are:</p><ul><li>Information, assets and services are safeguarded from compromise and employees are protected against 
workplace violence;</li><li>Governance structures, mechanisms and resources are in place to ensure effective and efficient management 
of security at both a departmental and government-wide level;</li><li>Management of security incidents is effectively coordinated within departments and government-wide;</li><li>Interoperability and information exchange are enabled through effective and consistent security and 
identity management practices; and</li><li>Continuity of government operations and services is maintained in the presence of security incidents, 
disruptions or emergencies.</li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="6" title="6. Requirements"><p>6.1 Deputy heads of all departments are responsible for:</p><div class="indent1"><p>6.1.1 Establishing a security program for the coordination and management of departmental security 
activities that:</p><ol class="lower-alpha"><li>Has a governance structure with clear accountabilities</li><li>Has defined objectives that are aligned with departmental and government-wide policies, priorities and 
plans; and</li><li>Is monitored, assessed and reported on to measure management efforts, resources and success toward achieving 
its expected results;</li></ol><p>6.1.2 Appointing a departmental security officer (<abbr title="Departmental Security Officer">DSO</abbr>) functionally responsible to the deputy head or to the departmental executive committee to manage the departmental security program (Note: The deputy head of a small department or agency (<abbr title="Small departments and agencies">SDA</abbr>) can assume the role of <abbr title="Departmental Security Officer">DSO</abbr>);</p><p>6.1.3 Establishing a formal arrangement with the service provider when the role of the <abbr title="Departmental Security Officer">DSO</abbr> is fulfilled by a third party (e.g., shared or clustered service provider or a portfolio department);</p><p>6.1.4 Approving the departmental security plan that details decisions for managing security risks and outlines strategies, goals, objectives, priorities and timelines for improving departmental security and supporting its implementation;</p><p>6.1.5 Ensuring that managers at all levels integrate security and identity management requirements 
into plans, programs, activities and services;</p><p>6.1.6 Ensuring that all individuals who will have access to government information and assets, 
including those who work in or for offices of Ministers and Ministers of State, are security screened at the appropriate 
level before the commencement of their duties and are treated in a fair and unbiased manner;</p><p>6.1.7 Ensuring that their authority to deny, revoke or suspend security clearances is not delegated;</p><p>6.1.8 Ensuring that when significant issues arise regarding policy compliance, allegations of 
misconduct, suspected criminal activity, security incidents, or workplace violence they are investigated, acted on and reported 
to the appropriate law enforcement authority, national security agency or lead security agency.</p></div><p>6.2 Deputy heads of lead security agencies are responsible for:</p><div class="indent1"><p>6.2.1 Providing departments with advice, guidance and services related to government security, 
consistent with their mandated responsibilities;</p><p>6.2.2 Appointing an executive or executives to coordinate and oversee the provision of support 
services to departments and to represent the deputy head to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> in this regard; and</p><p>6.2.3 Ensuring that the security support services provided help government departments achieve 
and maintain an acceptable state of security and readiness and that those services remain aligned with government-wide policies, 
priorities and plans related to government security.</p><ul><li>A list of lead security agencies and details on the nature and scope of their responsibilities 
under this policy are found in <a href="#appB">Appendix B—Responsibilities of Lead Security Agencies</a>.</li></ul></div><p>6.3 Monitoring and reporting requirements</p><p>Within departments</p><ul><li>Deputy heads are responsible for ensuring that periodic reviews are conducted to 
assess whether the departmental security program is effective, whether the goals, strategic objectives and control objectives 
detailed in their departmental security plan were achieved and whether their departmental security plan remains appropriate 
to the needs of the department and the government as a whole.</li></ul><p>By departments</p><ul><li>Deputy heads are responsible for reporting periodically to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>, on the status and 
progress of implementation of this policy and on the results of ongoing performance measurement.</li></ul><p>Lead security agencies</p><ul><li>In additional to monitoring and reporting on their departmental security program 
Deputy heads of lead security agencies are also responsible for:</li><li>Ensuring that periodic reviews are conducted to assess the effectiveness of their 
security support services to ensure they continue to meet the needs of departments and the government as a whole; and 
  </li><li>Reporting on their activities under this policy through current government reporting 
mechanisms, e.g., Management, Resources and Results Structure (<abbr title="Management Resources and Results Structure">MRRS</abbr>), departmental performance reports (<abbr title="Departmental Performance Report">DPR</abbr>) and reports 
on plans and priorities (<abbr title="Report on Plans and Priorities ">RPP</abbr>).</li></ul><p>Government-wide</p><ul><li><abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> is responsible for:<ul><li>Monitoring compliance with this policy and the achievement of expected results 
in a variety of ways, including but not limited to <abbr title="Management Accountability Framework">MAF</abbr> assessments, Treasury Board submissions, <abbr title="Departmental Performance Report">DPR</abbr>s, <abbr title="Report on Plans and Priorities ">RPP</abbr>s, results of audits, 
evaluations and studies, and ongoing dialogue and committee work; and</li><li>Reviewing and reporting to Treasury Board on the effectiveness and implementation 
of this policy and its directives and standards at the five-year mark from the effective date of the policy. Where substantiated 
by risk analysis, <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> will also ensure an evaluation is conducted.</li></ul></li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="7" title="7. Consequences"><p>7.1 The deputy head is responsible for ensuring appropriate remedial actions are taken to address issues regarding policy 
compliance, allegations of misconduct, suspected criminal activity or security incidents, including denying, revoking or 
suspending security clearances and reliability status, as appropriate.</p><p>7.2 If the Secretary of the Treasury Board determines that a department may not have complied with any requirement of 
this policy or its supporting directives or standards, the secretary of the Treasury Board may request that the deputy head:</p><div class="indent1"><p>7.2.1 Conduct an audit or a review, the cost of which will be paid from the department's reference 
level, to assess whether requirements of this policy or its supporting directives have been met; and/or</p><p>7.2.2 Take corrective actions and report back on the outcome.</p><p>7.2.3 Consequences of non-compliance with this policy and its supporting directives and standards 
or failure to take corrective actions requested by the secretary of the Treasury Board may include recommending to Treasury 
Board that measures deemed appropriate in the circumstances be imposed.</p></div></chapter><chapter anchor="8" title="8. References "><p>Legislation relevant to this policy includes the following:</p><ul><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/A-1/">Access to Information Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-5/">Canada Evidence Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/L-2/">Canada Labour Code</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-305/">Canada Occupational Health and Safety Regulations</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/charter/">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/H-6/index.html">Canadian Human Rights Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/C-23/index.html">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/C-46/">Criminal Code</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/C-47/index.html">Criminal Records Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/d-1/">Defence Production Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/E-22/index.html">Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/showtdm/cs/E-4.56">Emergency Management Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/F-8.4/index.html">Federal Real Property and Federal Immovables Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/f-11/">Financial Administration Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/I-21/index.html">Interpretation Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/L-7.7/index.html">Library and Archives of Canada Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/N-5/index.html">National Defence Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/P-21/index.html">Privacy Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/showtdm/cs/P-31.9">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/P-33.01/index.html">Public Service Employment Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/P-33.3/">Public Service Labour Relations Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/R-10/index.html">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://lois.justice.gc.ca/en/showtdm/cs/O-5">Security of Information Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://lois.justice.gc.ca/en/showtdm/cs/S-19">Statistics Act</a></em></li><li><em><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/en/Y-1.5/index.html">Youth Criminal Justice Act</a></em></li></ul><p>Treasury Board policies, directives and standards relevant to this policy include the following:</p><ul><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453">Access to Information, Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12316">Communications Policy of the Government of Canada</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14494">Contracting Policy</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12063">Controlled Goods Directive</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16579">Departmental Security Management, Directive on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15024">Evaluation, Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16577">Identity Management, Directive on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/ciopubs/TB_GIH/im-roles-gi_e.asp">Information Management Roles and 
  Responsibilities, Directive on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/fip-pcim/index-eng.asp">Federal Identity Program</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/RealProperty/CHAP2-5_e.asp">Fire Protection, Investigation 
  and Reporting, Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13616">Foundation Framework for Treasury Board Policies</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12452">Information and Technology, Policy Framework for</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/ciopubs/tb_gih/pim-pgi_e.asp">Information Management, 
  Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/RiskManagement/rmf-cgr_e.asp">Integrated Risk Management Framework</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/ia-vi/ia-vi_e.asp">Internal Audit, 
  Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15258">Internal Controls, Policy</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12405">Learning, Training, and Development, 
  Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/RealProperty/ltcp-pilt_e.asp">Long-term 
  Capital Plans, Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/TBM_142/4-7_e.asp">Losses of Money 
  and Offences and Other Illegal Acts Against the Crown, Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12022">Management of Assets and Acquired Services, Policy 
  Framework for the</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12084">Management of Compensation, Policy Framework for 
  the</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/ciopubs/tb_it/mit-gti_e.asp">Management of 
  Information Technology, Policy on </a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12062">Management of 
  Materiel, Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12042">Management of Real Property, 
  Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14252">Management, Resources and 
  Results Structure, Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12560">Occupational Safety and Health</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12521">Official Languages for Human Resources Management, 
  Policy on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12515">Official Languages Policy Framework</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/gospubs/TBM_12A/ossbcp-nsopca_e.asp">Operational Security Standard—Business 
  Continuity Planning (<abbr title="Business Continuity Planning">BCP</abbr>) Program</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/gospubs/TBM_12A/23RECON_e.asp">Operational Security Standard - Management 
  of Information Technology Security (<abbr title="Management of Information Technology Security">MITS</abbr>)</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/gospubs/TBM_12A/osps-nosm_e.asp">Operational Security Standard - Physical 
  Security</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/gospubs/TBM_12A/CHAPT2-4-1_e.asp">Personnel Security Standard</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510">Privacy Protection, Policy 
  on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/TBM_122/chapt2-2_e.asp">Project Management 
  Policy</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/dcgpubs/RiskManagement/riskmanagpol_e.asp">Risk Management, Policy 
  on</a></em></li><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/gospubs/TBM_12A/CHAPT2-5-1_e.asp#sec">Security and Contracting Management 
  Standard</a></em></li><li><a href="/pubs_pol/hrpubs/TB_851/vec-cve_e.asp"><em>The Values and Ethics Code for the Public 
  Service</em></a></li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="9" title="9. Enquiries"><p>Please direct enquiries about this policy to your <abbr title="Departmental Security Officer">DSO</abbr>. For interpretation of this policy, the <abbr title="Departmental Security Officer">DSO</abbr> should contact:</p><p>Security and Identity Management Division<br />
Chief Information Officer Branch<br />
Treasury Board Secretariat<br />
Ottawa ON K1A 0R5</p><p>Email: <a href="mailto:SIDM-SGID@tbs-sct.gc.ca" title="contact SIDM-SGID by email">SIDM-SGID@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a><br />
Telephone: (613) 946-5046<br />
Fax: (613) 952-7232<br />
Teletype: (613) 957-9090 (<abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>)</p></chapter></chapters><appendices><appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A—Definitions"><dl><dt><strong>availability</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>disponibilité</em></span>)</dt><dd>The state of being accessible and usable in a timely and reliable manner.</dd><dt><strong>business continuity planning</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>planification de la continuité des opérations</em></span>)</dt><dd>The development and timely execution of plans, measures, procedures and arrangements to ensure minimal or no interruption to the availability of critical services and assets.</dd><dt><strong>communications security (<abbr title="Communications security">COMSEC</abbr>)</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>sécurité des communications (<abbr title="Communications security">COMSEC</abbr>)</em></span>)</dt><dd>The application of cryptographic security, transmission and emission security, physical security measures, operational practices and controls to deny unauthorized access to information derived from telecommunications and that ensure the authenticity of such telecommunications.</dd><dt><strong>compromise</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>compromission</em></span>)</dt><dd>The unauthorized access to, disclosure, destruction, removal, modification, use or interruption of assets or information.</dd><dt><strong>confidentiality</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>confidentialité</em></span>)</dt><dd>A characteristic applied to information to signify that it can only be disclosed to authorized individuals to prevent injury to national or other interests.</dd><dt><strong>critical service</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>service essentiel</em></span>)</dt><dd>A service whose compromise in terms of availability or integrity would result in a high degree of injury to the health, safety, security or economic well-being of Canadians or to the effective functioning of the Government of Canada (<abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr>).</dd><dt><strong>department</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>ministère</em></span>)</dt><dd>All departments named in Schedule I, divisions or branches of the federal public administration set out in column I of Schedule I.1, corporations named in Schedule II, and portions of the federal public administration named in schedules IV and V of the Financial Administration Act (<abbr title="Financial Administration Act">FAA</abbr>), unless excluded by specific acts, regulations or Orders in Council.</dd><dt><strong>deputy head</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>administrateur général</em></span>)</dt><dd>Deputy Head as defined in section 11 of the <em>Financial Administrtion Act</em>, and in the case of the Canadian Forces the Chief of the Defence Staff.</dd><dt><strong>emergency</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>urgence</em></span>)</dt><dd>A present or imminent event, including <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> incidents, that requires prompt coordination of actions to protect the health, safety or welfare of people, or to limit damage to assets or the environment.</dd><dt><strong>emergency management</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>gestion des urgences</em></span>)</dt><dd>The prevention and mitigation of, preparedness for, response to and recovery from emergencies.</dd><dt><strong>executive</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>cadre supérieure</em></span>)</dt><dd>An employee appointed to the executive group (EX-01 to EX-05 levels), i.e., director, director general, assistant deputy minister or equivalent.</dd><dt><strong>identity</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>identité</em></span>)</dt><dd>A reference or designation used to distinguish a unique and particular individual, organization or device.</dd><dt><strong>identity management</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>gestion de l'identité</em></span>)</dt><dd>The set of principles, practices, processes and procedures used to realize an organization's mandate and its objectives related to identity.</dd><dt><strong>interoperability</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>interopérabilité</em></span>)</dt><dd>The ability of federal government departments to operate synergistically through consistent security and identity management practices.</dd><dt><strong>national interest</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>intérêt national</em></span>)</dt><dd>The security and the social, political and economic stability of Canada.</dd><dt><strong>reliability status</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>cote de fiabilité</em></span>)</dt><dd>Indicates the successful completion of reliability checks; allows regular access to government assets and with a need to know to PROTECTED information.</dd><dt><strong>risk</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>risque</em></span>)</dt><dd>The uncertainty that can create exposure to undesired future events and outcomes. It is the expression of the likelihood and impact of an event with the potential to impede the achievement of an organization's objectives.</dd><dt><strong>security clearance</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>cote de sécurité</em></span>)</dt><dd>indicates successful completion of a security assessment; with a need to know, allows access to classified information. There are three Security Clearance levels: Confidential, Secret and Top Secret.</dd><dt><strong>security control</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>mesure de sécurité</em></span>)</dt><dd>An administrative, operational, technical, physical or legal measure for managing security risk. This term is synonymous with safeguard.</dd><dt><strong>security incident</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>incident de sécurité</em></span>)</dt><dd>Any workplace violence toward an employee or any act, event or omission that could result in the compromise of information, assets or services.</dd><dt><strong>security screening</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>filtrage de sécurité</em></span>)</dt><dd>Any measure resulting in a high level of assurance that an individual can be granted specific access privileges within the context of the federal government.</dd><dt><strong>signals intelligence (<abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr>)</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>renseignement électromagnétique – <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr></em></span>)</dt><dd>Technical information or intelligence composed of (individually or in combination) communications intelligence (<abbr title="Communications Intelligence">COMINT</abbr>), electronic intelligence (<abbr title="Electronic Intelligence">ELINT</abbr>) and foreign instrumentation signals intelligence (<abbr title="Foreign Instrumentation Signals Intelligence">FISINT</abbr>).</dd><dt><strong>communications intelligence</strong> (<em><abbr title="Communications Intelligence">COMINT</abbr></em>)</dt><dd>Technical information or intelligence derived from the exploitation of communications systems, information technology systems and networks, and any data or technical information carried on, contained in or relating to those systems or networks by other than the intended recipient.</dd><dt><strong>electronic intelligence</strong> (<em><abbr title="Electronic Intelligence">ELINT</abbr></em>)</dt><dd>Technical information or intelligence derived from the collection, processing and analysis of electromagnetic non-communications emissions.</dd><dt><strong>foreign instrumentation signals intelligence</strong> (<em><abbr title="Foreign Instrumentation Signals Intelligence">FISINT</abbr></em>)</dt><dd>Technical information or intelligence derived from the collection, processing and analysis of foreign instrumentation signals by other than the intended recipient.</dd><dt><strong>situational awareness</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>connaissance de la situation</em></span>)</dt><dd>Having insight into one's environment and circumstances to understand how events and actions will affect business objectives, both now and in the near future. Having complete, accurate, and current SA is essential in any domain where technological complexity, decision making, and the well-being of the public interact. Because incident management involves predictions and forecasts, SA in the area of <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> requires an understanding of the interrelationships between critical services and information, safeguards supporting <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> infrastructure and processes, and evolving threats.</dd><dt><strong>sophisticated <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security incident</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>incident complexe de sécurité des TI</em></span>)</dt><dd>An event, usually initiated by sophisticated threat actors, that is complicated to detect and recover from, causes harm to <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> networks and systems, and affects the confidentiality, integrity and availability of information.</dd><dt><strong>sophisticated <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security threat</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>menace complexe à la sécurité des TI</em></span>)</dt><dd>An entity or entities that make use of advanced technologies and tradecraft to penetrate or bypass protective systems and security technologies without being detected.</dd><dt><strong>threat</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>menace</em></span>)</dt><dd>An event or act, deliberate or accidental, that could cause injury to people, information, assets or services.</dd><dt><strong>vulnerability</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>vulnérabilité</em></span>)</dt><dd>An inadequacy related to security that could increase susceptibility to compromise or injury.</dd><dt><strong>workplace violence</strong> (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>violence dans le lieu de travail</em></span>)</dt><dd>An action, conduct, threat or gesture that can reasonably be expected to cause harm, injury or illness to an employee in the workplace.</dd></dl></appendix><appendix anchor="B" title="Appendix B—Responsibilities of Lead Security Agencies"><p>Lead security agencies provide advice, guidance and services to support the day-to-day security operations of departments 
and enable government as a whole to effectively manage security activities, coordinate response to security incidents, and 
achieve and maintain an acceptable state of security and readiness. This appendix describes their responsibilities as they 
relate to their areas of expertise.</p><p><strong>Treasury Board Secretariat (<abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>)</strong> establishes and oversees a whole-of-government approach to security 
and identity management as a key component of all management activities and monitors the adequacy of services to support 
these activities and practices across government. <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Establishing and maintaining interdepartmental security governance to exercise 
strategic oversight of government security and providing leadership and recommending priorities related to:<ul><li>Government security policies and approaches to security community development,</li><li>Establishment of standards and designation of the necessary authorities for identifying 
and authenticating individuals internal and external to the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr>,</li><li>Security services provided by lead security agencies, 
and</li><li>Incident management (including preparedness, mitigation, response, recovery and 
post-incident analysis activities related to security);</li></ul></li><li>Setting government-wide direction, establishing priorities, and defining and formalizing 
security and identity management requirements for the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> and departments;</li><li>Setting government-wide direction and defining requirements for the personal record 
identifier (PRI) and the individual agency number (IAN);</li><li>Providing guidance to lead security agencies on training and awareness strategies 
and coordinating training and awareness programs for the development of the security and identity communities, security 
practitioners, managers at all levels and other functional communities;</li><li>Establishing and leading <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> security and identity community forums and events to 
support departments in implementing the <em>Policy on Government Security;</em></li><li>Establishing service standards, in collaboration with lead security agencies, related 
to the provision of advice, guidance and services to support the implementation of the <em>Policy on Government Security</em> 
and monitor its progress toward achievement of desired outcomes;</li><li>Maintaining close links with Public Safety Canada, monitoring and evaluating its 
information products to identify incidents that may have public service implications, and making recommendations concerning 
the activation of emergency and incident response plans;</li><li>Providing direction and advice to lead security agencies and departments on the 
approach and implementation of measures for managing security incidents, including incidents affecting government security, 
operation of government <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> systems and networks, service delivery and confidence in government; and</li><li>Providing oversight of incident management to ensure the government's strategic 
objectives are maintained. This includes, but is not limited to, performing post-mortem reviews on incident management activities, 
tracking the status of after-incident action reports, and developing lessons learned.</li></ul><p><strong>Privy Council Office (<abbr title="Privy Council Office">PCO</abbr>)</strong> advises and supports the prime minister and Cabinet on national security 
matters and coordinates the related activities of departments and agencies. <abbr title="Privy Council Office">PCO</abbr> is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Providing government-wide policy direction on national security and intelligence 
priorities;</li><li>Advising departments on strategies, mechanisms and activities required to develop, 
implement, evaluate and improve a fully integrated security system in the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> in support of national security objectives;</li><li>Providing direction to Public Safety Canada to help resolve government security 
incidents and events that may affect national security;</li><li>Providing direction and advice to departments and agencies on implementing security 
readiness levels in emergency and increased threat situations;</li><li>Supporting the Prime Minister in establishing candidates' fitness for office for 
public office positions and conducting security clearances for deputy heads;</li><li>Providing direction and advice to departments and agencies on the level of security 
support to be provided to ministers, secretaries of State and parliamentary secretaries; and</li><li>Establishing government policy on the security of Cabinet Confidences (i.e., Confidences 
of the Queen's Privy Council for Canada) and of records administered under the Cabinet Papers System and coordinating the 
investigation into unauthorized disclosure or other compromise of those documents.</li></ul><p><strong>Public Safety Canada (PS)</strong> coordinates activities related to emergencies (which include <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> incidents) 
affecting the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> and provides leadership in the area of emergency management, which includes continuity of operations and 
<abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> incident management. PS is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Establishing policies, standards and programs for emergency management;</li><li>Providing advice and guidance to departments in developing situational awareness through the identification 
of information, assets and facilities that support critical services and government operations and defining dependencies 
and interdependencies to:<ul><li>Help improve the government's preparedness and response capability,</li><li>Manage emergencies, and</li><li>Support federal decision making;</li></ul></li><li>Providing advice and guidance to departments for the preparation, maintenance, 
testing and implementation of emergency management and business continuity plans;</li><li>Providing central coordination for assessing emerging complex threats and developing 
and promoting comprehensive, coordinated approaches to address risks within the federal government and across Canada;</li><li>Developing and implementing emergency management training and learning programs 
and strategies for federal communities;</li><li>Sharing lessons learned and best practices with emergency management practitioners 
and facilitating the sharing of information within the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> and between the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> and its relevant partners;</li><li>Coordinating the development of national and regional level emergency management 
exercises and providing advice and guidance to departments on those on exercises;</li><li>Promoting awareness of emergency management matters and facilitating the sharing 
of information to enhance emergency and incident management;</li><li>Issuing information, advice and guidance to the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> on emergency management;</li><li>Representing the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> on regional, national and international initiatives related 
to emergency management;</li><li>Communicating <abbr title="Privy Council Office">PCO</abbr> direction requiring departments and agencies to implement a readiness 
level in response to security threats;</li><li>Monitoring potential, imminent and actual emergencies, including those significantly 
affecting <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr>, advising other departments and <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> accordingly and coordinating the management of emergencies that affect 
or may affect services to Canadians, government operations or the effective functioning of government. Under this function, 
PS is responsible for:</li><li>Monitoring threats to services to Canadians, government operations or the effective function of government, 
including but not limited to government networks, information systems and other critical infrastructure, issuing advice, 
guidance and situational awareness reports to departments on potential or actual emergencies and coordinating the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> response 
to and recovery from an emergency;</li><li>Responding to requests from government departments for specific technical advice, guidance and information 
on <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> incident response and recovery;</li><li>Developing post-incident analysis and after-action reports and recommending actions 
to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and departments to mitigate future incidents; and</li><li>Reporting to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> throughout all phases of incident management with its analysis 
of events and incidents that have or may have affected services to Canadians, government operations or the effective functioning 
of government.</li></ul><p><strong>Communications Security Establishment Canada (CSEC)</strong> provides leadership and coordination for departmental 
activities that help ensure the protection of electronic information and information systems of importance and serves as 
the government's national authority for <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr> and <abbr title="Communications security">COMSEC</abbr>. CSEC is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Developing, based on analysis of community needs and in partnership with <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>, policy 
instruments related to information technology (<abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr>) security for approval by <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>;</li><li>Developing, approving and promulgating <abbr title="Communications security">COMSEC</abbr>- and <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr>-related policy instruments 
for classified information and developing guidelines and tools related to <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security;</li><li>Coordinating the development and provision of training and awareness related to 
<abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security, <abbr title="Communications security">COMSEC</abbr> and <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr> to DSOs, security practitioners and, as required, other authorized individuals;</li><li>Leading <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security-related interdepartmental committees and working groups and 
facilitating the sharing of information and collaboration across security communities;</li><li>Collecting and reviewing <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security best practices and making recommendations 
to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and security governance committees to facilitate security policy improvements and collaboration among departments;</li><li>Conducting research on <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security methods, technologies or common services and 
proposing solutions to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and governance committees to improve risk management and economies of scale in government;</li><li>Authorizing special <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr> compartment indoctrinations and maintaining a national 
inventory for personnel cleared and indoctrinated in <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr>;</li><li>Authorize the operation of <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> systems and facilities handling <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr>;</li><li>Responding to and participate in the investigation or analysis of sophisticated 
<abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security incidents, threats and vulnerabilities and acting on information collected or received from these investigations;</li><li>Providing advice and guidance to departments on the:<ul><li>Protection and distribution of <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr>,</li><li>Use and application of <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security products, <abbr title="Communications security">COMSEC</abbr> devices, cryptographic measures and key management,</li><li>Certification of shared and common <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> services, emerging <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security technologies, ITS architecture 
design, common ITS solutions, including secure use of commercial-off-the-shelf products, system and network security design, 
and security posture and vulnerability assessments,</li><li>Design and upgrade of <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr><abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> infrastructures and their security interconnectivities</li><li>Application of <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> access controls for confidentiality and integrity as well as threat detection and 
prevention, and</li><li>Certification of <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> shared, common or federated <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> services;</li></ul></li><li>Providing services to departments for:<ul><li>Key management systems and related components for classified information,</li><li>Predicting, preventing and defending against sophisticated <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security incidents, threats and vulnerabilities,</li><li>Handling and mitigation of sophisticated <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security incidents,</li><li>Security architecture design for <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> shared, common or federated initiatives,</li><li><abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security product assessment and/or approval for products in use in classified domain when deemed 
necessary,</li><li>Tailored engineering and operational support for information infrastructure projects of importance 
to the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr>, and</li><li><abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> systems and facilities certification and accreditation for handling <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr>;</li></ul></li><li>Developing procurement vehicles, in partnership with the Department of Public Works 
and Government Services (<abbr title="Public Works and Government Services Canada ">PWGSC</abbr>), for pre-qualified <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security products and services;</li><li>Gathering, analyzing and facilitating the authorized sharing of consolidated <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> 
security threat and vulnerability information with departments and with Public Safety Canada; and</li><li>Representing the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> on national and international initiatives related to <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security 
and <abbr title="Signals intelligence">SIGINT</abbr>.</li></ul><p><strong>Public Works and Government Services Canada (<abbr title="Public Works and Government Services Canada ">PWGSC</abbr>) </strong>provides leadership and coordination of activities 
to help ensure the application of security safeguards through all phases of the contracting process within the scope of 
the industrial security program (ISP). It also provides services related to physical security respecting the <abbr title="Public Works and Government Services Canada ">PWGSC</abbr> Real 
Property Program and common services related to <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security for increased efficiency and economy of the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr>. <abbr title="Public Works and Government Services Canada ">PWGSC</abbr> is responsible 
for:</p><ul><li>Delivering services within the scope of the Industrial Security Program, including:<ul><li>Developing, based on analysis of community needs, in partnership with <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>, policy 
instruments, guidelines and tools related to security in contracting for approval by <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>;</li><li>Coordinating the development and provision of training and awareness related to 
security in contracting;</li><li>Leading interdepartmental committees and working groups for security in contracting 
to facilitate the sharing of information and collaboration across communities of practice;</li><li>Collecting and reviewing best practices related to security in contracting and 
making recommendations to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and security governance committees to facilitate security policy improvements and collaboration 
among departments;</li><li>Maintaining a database of private sector organizations and individuals that have 
been authorized to access classified and protected information and assets;</li><li>Carrying out roles pursuant to international agreements respecting industrial security; </li><li>Conducting security inspections of companies that have access to protected and 
classified information and assets of NATO allies or those who are registered with countries with which Canada has reciprocal 
Industrial Security Memoranda of Understanding;</li><li>Processing requests for visits when a security cleared individual must visit a 
government/commercial organization in Canada or abroad;</li><li>Performing the necessary security screening of private sector individuals and organizations 
that have access to protected and classified information and assets, including those participating in foreign contracts;</li><li>Ensuring compliance in those security contracts that afford industry access to 
government information and assets;</li><li>Controlling and managing <abbr title="Communications security">COMSEC</abbr> assets in private sector companies and providing 
screening clearances and inspections for <abbr title="Communications security">COMSEC</abbr> assets in private sector companies;</li><li>Representing the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> on national and international initiatives related to security 
in contracting and controlled goods;</li></ul></li><li>Delivering services related to <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security, including:<ul><li>Providing common <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> security services and other solutions to enable departments to exchange information 
with citizens, businesses and employees;</li><li>Ensuring the confidentiality, integrity and availability of common <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> services provided to departments; </li><li>Gathering, analyzing, consolidating and facilitating the sharing of operational threat and vulnerability 
information related to common <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> services and government <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> critical infrastructure managed by <abbr title="Public Works and Government Services Canada ">PWGSC</abbr> and communicating the 
information to Public Safety Canada and, as authorized, to departments;</li></ul></li><li>Delivering services related to physical security, including:<ul><li>Providing base building security for general-purpose office accommodation for which <abbr title="Public Works and Government Services Canada ">PWGSC</abbr> is the 
building custodian; and</li><li>Procuring security guard services from the Canadian Corps of Commissionaires under the National Master 
Standing Offer for Commissionaire Services or from other service providers as appropriate;</li></ul></li><li>Delivering other services, including:<ul><li>Issuing unique personal record identifiers (PRI) to departments and agencies, and 
individual agency numbers (IAN) to agencies outside the federal public service, upon request;</li><li>Maintaining the PRI and IAN systems, under the direction and guidance of the Treasury 
Board Secretariat; and</li><li>Coordinating the procurement of goods and services for all government departments 
during emergencies</li></ul></li></ul><p><strong>Canadian Security Intelligence Service (<abbr title="Canadian Security Intelligence Service">CSIS</abbr>)</strong> collects, investigates, analyzes and retains information 
and intelligence that may be suspected of constituting threats to the security of Canada and provides security assessments 
to departments within its statutory mandate. <abbr title="Canadian Security Intelligence Service">CSIS</abbr> is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Developing, based on analysis of community needs and in partnership with <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>, policy 
instruments, guidelines and tools related to personnel security screening for approval by <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>;</li><li>Participating in the development of training and awareness related to personnel 
security screening;</li><li>Conducting investigations and providing security assessments in support of personnel 
security screenings to appraise loyalty to Canada, and so far as it relates thereto, the reliability of an individual 
</li><li>Maintaining a central index of security assessments and a national central registry 
of information and documentation that it receives on all persons who are "permanently bound to secrecy" as defined in the
<em>Security of Information Act</em>;</li><li>Providing intelligence reports and assessments to the government on threats to 
the security of Canada, including issues relating to terrorism, espionage, clandestine foreign-influenced activities and 
economic security, and assessments relating to cyber security to help ensure the protection of the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr>'s critical services 
and systems;</li><li>Conducting comprehensive and integrated analysis of all available threat information 
to build situational awareness for governmental decision makers. Under this function, <abbr title="Canadian Security Intelligence Service">CSIS</abbr> is required to:<ul><li>Assemble and analyze intelligence about potential threats from a wide range of 
sources and make the results of that analysis available to all <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> representatives requiring it (e.g., DSOs and security 
practitioners);</li><li>Support, through its assessments, the security postures to be developed by governmental 
first responders, which include police forces and emergency management organizations;</li><li>Provide a unified and comprehensive threat picture related to special events involving 
the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr>;</li><li>Support comprehensive threat and risk assessments related to the protection of 
services to Canadians, government operations and confidence in government; and</li><li>Provide information to Public Safety Canada to aid in emergency and <abbr title="Information Technology">IT</abbr> incident 
management.</li></ul></li></ul><p><strong>Royal Canadian Mounted Police (<abbr title="Royal Canadian Mounted Police ">RCMP</abbr>)</strong> provides leadership and coordination for departmental activities 
that help ensure the physical protection of government information, assets, facilities and people and provides services 
related to crime prevention, personnel screening, policing, law enforcement and investigations. <abbr title="Royal Canadian Mounted Police "><abbr title="Royal Canadian Mounted Police ">RCMP</abbr></abbr> is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Developing, based on analysis of community needs, policy instruments, guidelines, 
and tools related to physical security for approval by <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>;</li><li>Coordinating the development and provision of training and awareness related to 
physical security for DSOs, security practitioners and other functional communities (e.g., program managers, accommodation 
and materiel management specialists and contractors);</li><li>Leading interdepartmental committees and working groups for physical security to 
facilitate the sharing of information and collaboration within the community of practice;</li><li>Collecting and reviewing best practices for physical security and making recommendations 
to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and security governance committees to facilitate security policy improvements and collaboration among departments;</li><li>Coordinating research on physical security and personnel security screening and 
proposing solutions to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and governance committees to enable government to better manage risks and improve economies of 
scale;</li><li>Providing advice and guidance to departments on:<ul><li>Physical protection of government documents, assets and facilities, including facilities design,</li><li>Physical security equipment, systems, procedures and countermeasures,</li><li>Application of physical access controls, media disposal and system monitoring, and</li><li>Major events;</li></ul></li><li>Providing services for:<ul><li>Reviewing and advising on counter-technical intrusion detection,</li><li>Criminal investigations, including computer forensics and cyber crime,</li><li>Personnel security screening, including fingerprint and criminal records checks and, when there are 
reasonable grounds, conducting law enforcement assessments and advising departments on the results, and</li><li>Safeguarding designated persons from threats or acts of violence;</li></ul></li><li>Gathering, analyzing, consolidating and facilitating the sharing of operational 
threat and vulnerability information related to identity crime, physical security, cyber crime and other relevant criminal 
activity and communicating it to Public Safety Canada, <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and, as authorized, departments; and</li><li>Representing the <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> on national and international initiatives related to crime 
prevention and physical security.</li></ul><p><strong>Library and Archives of Canada (LAC)</strong> provides leadership and coordinates among government departments 
to help ensure the preservation of government information and records. LAC is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Developing, based on analysis of community and government needs and in partnership 
with <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and Public Safety Canada, guidelines and tools related to the management of information resources for business 
continuity purposes, for approval by <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr>;</li><li>Advising on the management of information resources for business continuity purposes 
for <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> departments;</li><li>Providing secure storage and management for the protection of the essential records 
of <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> institutions during emergencies;</li><li>Monitoring, reporting, and proposing joint strategies to acquire records at risk 
of serious damage or destruction that are essential for the continuity of <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> operations and services in order to properly 
preserve them for the long term; and</li><li>Participating in and advising on emergency response for the continuity of <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> operations 
and services.</li></ul><p><strong>Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade (<abbr title="Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade">DFAIT</abbr>)</strong> is the lead department for conducting 
foreign relations and the NATO National Security Authority for Canada. <abbr title="Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade">DFAIT</abbr> is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Arranging and coordinating physical security for <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> employees and assets housed 
at Canadian diplomatic and consular missions abroad;</li><li>Providing advice to departments and ensuring periodic and appropriate inspections 
of security arrangements for the protection and security of NATO's classified information in Canada;</li><li>Arranging and coordinating security for official visitors at <abbr title="Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade">DFAIT</abbr> facilities; </li><li>Providing advice to departments to help ensureadequate safeguards for the transmittal 
and transport of assets abroad and security initiatives with foreign governments and international organizations;</li><li>Providing diplomatic reporting and assessments to the government on political and 
other developments abroad that impact on the security of Canadian Government assets and personnel;</li><li>Providing diplomatic courier services for secure movement and safeguarding of classified 
information and assets between Canada and missions abroad;</li><li>Ensuring the confidentiality, integrity and availability of official communications 
transmitted by electronic means between departments and Canadian diplomatic missions abroad;</li><li>Conducting personnel security screening of locally engaged staff and other government 
officialsnot falling within the mandate of the <em>Interdepartmental Memorandum of Understanding on Operations and Support 
at Missions Abroad</em>; and</li><li>Coordinating activities at missions abroad during national or international emergencies.</li></ul><p><strong>Department of National Defence (DND) / Canadian Forces (CF)</strong></p><p>DND / CF are responsible for:</p><ul><li>Providing military intelligence for threat and risk assessment purposes; 
and</li><li>Arranging and coordinating security for any foreign military personnel visiting 
Canada or otherwise present at a defence facility.</li></ul><p><strong>Canada School of Public Service (CSPS)</strong></p><p>CSPS is responsible for:</p><ul><li>Providing training and educational services to help ensure that all public 
service employees have the knowledge and skills they need to deliver results for Canadians; and</li><li>Developing, delivering and regularly updating, in collaboration with <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> and lead 
security agencies, courses and programs that meet the needs of the functional security and identity management communities, 
assessing whether participants successfully complete them and reporting the results to <abbr title="Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">TBS</abbr> on an annual basis.</li></ul></appendix></appendices></doc>