<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Guideline on Interest and Administrative Charges" documentID="19024" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PolicyInstrumentSchema.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="1. Effective date"><p>1.1 This guideline takes effect on July 1, 2010.</p><p>1.2 It replaces the bulletin on the <em>Interest and Administrative
	Charges Regulations – TB Circular 1996-03 </em>dated April 29, 1996.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="2. Application"><p>This guideline applies to departments as defined in
	section 2 of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial
	Administration Act</em></a> (FAA). </p><p>Although the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/en/ShowDoc/cr/SOR-96-188/20090915/en?noCookie"><em>Interest and Administrative Charges Regulations</em></a>
	(hereafter "the Regulations") apply to all departments and agencies of the
	federal government and to amounts owing to departments by Crown corporations
	and provincial and foreign governments, they do not apply to the receivables of
	Crown corporations or to interdepartmental receivables.  </p><p>Part I of the Regulations, concerning the charging of interest, does not apply to:</p><ul><li>amounts owed as taxes or duties; </li><li>amounts owed under interest-bearing loans,
		capital market transactions or mortgages, except for concessionary loans as
		described in subsection 7(1); and </li><li>amounts for which other Acts, regulations, orders, contracts or
		arrangements provide the charging of interest on those amounts.</li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="3" title="3. Context"><p>3.1 The purpose of this guideline is to assist departmental officials
	with charging interest on overdue non-tax receivables and charging administrative
	fees when any instrument payable to the Crown is dishonoured.  </p><p>3.2 This guideline supports the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/en/ShowDoc/cr/SOR-96-188/20090915/en?noCookie"><em>Interest
	and Administrative Charges Regulations</em></a>.  </p><p>3.3 The Regulations help ensure that debtors have an incentive to pay
	their accounts on time and also permit the government to charge administrative
	fees when dishonoured payment instruments are received.</p><p>3.4 Though this guideline complements the Regulations, it does not
	present new mandatory requirements; rather, it reflects existing statutory and
	regulatory obligations.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="4" title="4. Charging interest and issuing invoices"><p>In keeping with sound business practices, bills, invoices and statements
	issued by departmental officials are to include payment terms, lists or
	schedules of applicable fees and rates, and note that interest will be charged
	on late payments.  Proper implementation of subsection 5.(1) of the Regulations
	requires that monthly statements issued for overdue accounts explicitly state
	that the payment due date remains the original due date and not 30 days from
	the statement's issuance.  Otherwise, no interest would accrue. Monthly
	statements should show the previous balance as well.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="5" title="5. General description of the regulations"><p>This section describes the main features of the Regulations. </p><p>5.1 When an account is overdue or a payment is late, departmental officials will charge interest compounded
	monthly at the average bank rate plus three per cent (3%) from the due date to
	the day before the date that payment is received; (this is the same interest rate
	that the government pays its suppliers for its own late payments.)</p><p>5.2 When the government makes overpayments or erroneous payments as a
	result of fraud, falsification, wilful misrepresentation or any other offence,
	these payments will incur interest charges from the date on which the
	overpayment or erroneous payment is made;</p><p>5.3 In other cases of government overpayment or erroneous payment,
	arrangements will be made for repayment and departmental officials will charge
	interest only when repayment is overdue;</p><p>5.4 Departmental officials are not to charge interest on small
	amounts for which an invoice or other demand for payment is normally not be
	issued.  However, if there are several small amounts that total more than the
	cut-off limit, or the total outstanding exceeds that limit, departmental
	officials are to charge interest.  Because each department sets its own
	cut-off  limits, limits may vary among departments and between programs within
	a department;</p><p>5.5 Ministers may waive or reduce charges under certain circumstances, such as the following:</p><ul><li>When charges will be
		recovered from subsequent entitlements,</li><li>When the government makes
		an error in processing a payment or in calculating the amount due; or</li><li>When there are other circumstances beyond the
		control of the debtor, such as a breakdown in the electronic systems used to
		transfer funds and process payments;</li></ul><p>5.6 An administrative charge of $25 will be levied when dishonoured
	items are processed by a financial institution and departmental officials have
	to requisition and issue a Receiver General payment instrument to reimburse the
	financial institution.  If the financial institution recovers the amount by
	another means, the administrative charge is $15;</p><p>5.7 Departmental officials may also arrange with a financial
	institution to monitor the account of a debtor who has tendered a dishonoured
	item and, once the account contains sufficient funds, to certify the item,
	return it to the department or clear the item directly.  Departmental officials
	may charge the debtor for fees it pays to a financial institution to monitor
	his or her account; and</p><p>5.8 Subject to any legislation or regulations governing programs or
	departments, departmental officials have complete flexibility in negotiating
	and setting repayment terms.  Under subsection 6(3) of the Regulations, departmental
	officials may charge interest on the total amount outstanding and not just on
	missed or late payments.  This is particularly appropriate when the debt
	involves an overpayment by the government that was not the result of an error
	on its part.  To charge interest on the total amount outstanding, departmental
	officials are to include an interest provision in the repayment agreement, </p></chapter><chapter anchor="" title="6. Special considerations"><section anchor="6.1" title="6.1 Accountable advances"><p>Though not explicitly stated, the
		Regulations suggest that interest may be charged on specific purpose and
		standing advances that are not settled within the time period specified in the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/SOR-86-438/index.html"><em>Accountable
		Advances Regulations</em></a>. </p><p>In the case of a trip or other
		specific purpose advance, the settlement period is 10 working days after
		fulfilment of the purpose for which the advance was made. In the case of a
		standing advance, the settlement period is 30 days from when a demand for
		repayment is received and or within 30 days following the end of the fiscal
		year, whichever is first. </p><p>The recipient of an accountable
		advance is to have either receipts for expenditures incurred (when receipts are
		required) or the cash.  </p><p>The "10-day rule"
		applies only to the initial accounting and repayment.  It is satisfied when the
		claim and amount owing (if any) is submitted, not when it is approved or
		audited.  If a travel claim is audited and adjusted, and the advance holder
		owes an additional amount, this becomes a normal debt due to the Crown.  The
		standard 30-day collection period would apply, unless the department specifies
		otherwise in its notice to the advance holder.</p><p>Under the Regulations, interest is
		payable only on the amount owing the government, not on the total advance
		outstanding.  If the advance holder does not file a claim, however, the amount
		owing the government is the amount of the advance.</p><p>When advance holders are late in
		filing their claims, departments are to notify them promptly that interest is
		accruing.  For practical purposes, it may be necessary to wait until the claim
		is actually filed before billing and recording interest unless the claim has
		not been filed within 30 days of the required filing date.</p><p>When extenuating circumstances
		prevented the advance holder from filing his or her claim on time, or the
		interest accrued is a small amount, departments may consider a waiver under
		paragraphs 8(1)(b) or 9(1)(a) or subsection 9(2) of the regulations.</p><p>There is currently no authority
		under either collective agreements or the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/travel-voyage/index-eng.php"><em>Travel
		Directive</em></a> for the government to pay interest on amounts it owes the
		advance holder.  </p></section><section anchor="6.2" title="6.2 Concessionary loans"><p>A concessionary loan is a loan
		made at no interest or at rates significantly below "market."  A
		developing country is usually the borrower, although some loans to employees
		and First Nations and other housing loans may fall into this category as well.</p><p>When a repayment of a
		concessionary loan is in default, the "concession" is rescinded for
		the amount that is in arrears.  Under the Regulations, interest at the "going"
		rate and not the concessionary rate would apply to those arrears. For example,
		if the concessionary rate is three per cent and the current "going" rate is
		seven, then an additional four per cent over and above the initial three would
		be payable on any arrears.  However, this does not apply to loans to developing
		nations that are the subject of multilateral debt-relief agreements, like the "Paris Club" arrangements, or to agreements that already provide for interest on the
		arrears, in accordance with subsection 155.1(1) of the FAA.</p></section><section anchor="6.3" title="6.3 Errors by the government"><p>Under paragraph 8(1)(a) and
		section 11 of the Regulations, a department is not to apply interest or
		administrative charges when it makes an error that results in interest or
		administrative charges otherwise being applicable—for example, if it does not
		credit the right account, does not deposit or record the payment promptly,
		attempts to deposit a post-dated cheque early, or holds a cheque until it
		becomes stale-dated.</p></section><section anchor="6.4" title="6.4 Goods and services tax (GST) and harmonized sales Tax (HST)"><p>The GST/HST does not apply to
		interest and administrative fees imposed under these Regulations.</p></section><section anchor="6.5" title="6.5 Payment receipt date"><p>A payment's receipt date is
		either the day on which the payment is made at a financial institution or when
		it first arrives in the department.  Hence, departments are to date-stamp or
		batch all incoming payments by date received and use that date in calculating
		any interest due.</p></section><section anchor="6.6" title="6.6 Recoveries from contractors and suppliers"><p>If the government has overpaid a
		contractor or supplier and has demanded repayment, interest would apply if the
		contractor or supplier does not repay as specified in the demand. </p></section><section anchor="6.7" title="6.7 Non-sufficient funds (NSF) charges"><p>For the most part, departments
		use Receiver General concentrator accounts for deposits and financial
		institutions obtain reimbursement for dishonoured items through charge-back. 
		In such cases, no Receiver General payment is issued and the NSF charge would
		be $15.  However, if a payment or settlement is to be issued because either the
		department is not using a concentrator account or chargeback is not possible, then
		section 10(2) of the Regulations applies and the NSF charge is $25.</p></section><section anchor="6.8" title="6.8 Individual versus class waivers"><p>Waivers under subsections 9(1)
		and 12(1) can be either on an individual or a class basis; those under 9(2) and
		12(2) must be on an individual basis.</p></section><section anchor="6.9" title="6.9 Penalty waivers"><p>A waiver under paragraph 9(1)(d)
		does not require that the penalty match exactly the interest that would have
		been charged.  However, if the penalty is significantly less, perhaps the
		waiver should not be used.  Both interest and penalty could be imposed, as the Revenue
		Canada Agency does for tax fraud or evasion.</p></section><section anchor="" title="6.10 Effect of waiver"><p>Under subsections 155.1(4) and (5)
		of the FAA, if departments have waive (or reduce) interest or administrative
		charges, then no amount  (or the reduced amount) is payable.  In such cases,
		there would be nothing to write off. If something has been recorded in the
		accounts, an adjusting entry must be made to reverse or reduce it.</p></section><section anchor="6.11" title="6.11 Debt write-off"><p>When departments write off a debt
		as uncollectible, they will have to write off the accrued or accumulated
		interest too.  However, if the department ever resumes collection action,
		interest would be reinstated to the date of the write-off unless it was forgiven
		or remitted.</p></section><section anchor="6.12" title="6.12 Spending of interest revenue"><p>In most cases, departments do not
		currently pay interest on their use of capital. The Department of Finance
		absorbs these costs as part of the public debt and does not charge them back to
		departments' programs.</p><p>Because departments are not
		incurring the interest expense for the use of capital, they must not treat
		revenue from interest charges on overdue receivables as additional funds to
		spend. Rather, they must account for such interest revenue as general, non-tax
		revenue to "offset" the Department of Finance's cost of financing the
		receivables.</p><p>However, if a department does
		incur costs by paying interest on its use of capital, which is in the case with
		some revolving funds, the interest charged on receivables may be offset against
		those costs.</p><p>Similarly, revolving funds and
		departments with appropriate net-voting authority may use the administrative
		charges to offset the handling costs incurred where a payment instrument is
		dishonoured.</p></section><section anchor="6.13" title="6.13 Obtaining information on current interest rates"><p>The interest rate applicable to
		Government of Canada overdue supplier accounts can be obtained from the
		Receiver General (RG) <a href="http://www.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/recgen/txt/71-eng.html">Payment on Due Date
		(PODD)</a> web page.</p></section></chapter><chapter anchor="7" title="7. References"><p>For additional information regarding legislative and
	policy aspects of charging interest and administrative charges, the following
	may be consulted.</p><section anchor="7.1" title="7.1 Other relevant legislation and regulations:"><ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a>,
			section 155.1</li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/sor-96-188/"><em>Interest and
			Administrative Charges Regulations</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/SOR-86-438/index.html">Accountable
			Advances Regulations</a></li></ul></section><section anchor="7.2" title="7.2 Related policy instruments and publications:"><ul><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17063"><em>Directive on
			Receivables Management</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15258"><em>Policy on Internal
			Control</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784"><em>Directive on Payment
			Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a></li></ul></section></chapter><chapter anchor="8" title="8. Enquiries"><p>Please direct enquiries concerning this guideline to
	your departmental headquarters. For interpretation of this guideline,
	departmental headquarters should contact:</p><p>Financial Management Policy Division<br />
	Financial Management and Analysis Sector<br />
	Office of the Comptroller General<br />
	Treasury Board Secretariat<br />
	Ottawa ON K1A 0R5</p><p>E-mail: <a href="mailto:fin-www@tbs-sct.gc.ca" title="Contact Financial Management Policy Division by email">fin-www@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a><br />
	Telephone: 613-957-7233<br />
	Facsimile: 613-952-9613</p></chapter></chapters><appendices><appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A—Interest rate calculation and interest calculation examples"><h3>Interest rate calculation</h3><p>The interest rate
used to calculate the interest payable on overdue accounts is the same as the
rate used under the Payment on Due Date Policy.  This rate is available on the <a href="http://www.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/recgen/txt/71-eng.html">Payment
on Due Date (PODD)</a> webpage.</p><p>The rate can also
be calculated by adding 3 per cent to the average bank rate of the month
preceding the month for which interest is being calculated.  A recorded message
at 613-782-7506 gives cuurent Bank of Canada rates.  </p><p>In the following example assume that the bank rates were as follows:</p><ul class="noBullet"><li class="noWrap">February 22: 5.5%</li><li class="noWrap">March 21: 5.25%</li></ul><p>Calculation of the
average bank rate for March would be based on 20 days (March 1 to 20 inclusive)
at 5.5% and 11 days (March 21 to 31 inclusive) at 5.25%:</p><ul class="noBullet fontSize80"><li class="noWrap">(20 days <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 5.5% <strong>[Plus]</strong> 11 days <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 5.25%) <strong>[Divide by]</strong> 31 days = 5.41%</li></ul><p>Therefore, the
interest rate used during the month of April to calculate interest on overdue
accounts would be:</p><ul class="noBullet"><li class="noWrap">5.41% <strong>[Plus]</strong> 3% = 8.41%</li></ul><h3>Interest calculation examples</h3><p>In the following
examples assume that the interest rate for May is 8.55%, the rate for June is
8.45%, the initial amount owing is $5,000 and the due date is April 30.  </p><ol class="lower-alpha"><li>If payment is made in full on April 30, no
interest is payable.</li><li>If payment is made in full on May 14, then
interest is payable on $5,000 for 14 days (April 30 to May 13 inclusive) and on
zero dollars for 1 day (May 14);  note that interest is charged on the
outstanding balance on each day, from the due date to the payment date
inclusive:

	<ul class="noBullet fontSize85"><li class="noWrap"><p>(14 days <strong>[Divide by]</strong> 365) <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 8.55% <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> $5,000 = $16.40</p></li><li class="noWrap"><p>(1 day <strong>[Divide by]</strong> 365) <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 8.55% <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> zero dollars = 0</p></li></ul></li><li>If partial payment of $3,000 is made on May
14 and another partial payment of $600 on May 24, then the amount owing on June
1 would be the interest on $5,000 for 14 days (April 30 to May 13 inclusive)
plus interest on $2,000 for 10 days (May 14 to 23 inclusive) plus interest on
$1,400 for 8 days (May 24 to 31 inclusive) plus the outstanding principal
amount of $1,400:<br /><ul class="noBullet fontSize85"><li class="noWrap"><p>(14 days <strong>[Divide by]</strong> 365) <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 8.55% <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> $5,000 = $16.40</p></li><li class="noWrap"><p>(10 days <strong>[Divide by]</strong> 365) <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 8.55% <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> $2,000 = $4.68</p></li><li class="noWrap"><p>(8 days <strong>[Divide by]</strong> 365) <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 8.55% <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> $1,400 = $2.62</p></li><li class="noWrap"><p>Outstanding principal amount = $1,400</p></li><li class="noWrap"><p>Total owing as of June 1 = $1,423.70</p></li></ul></li><li>If another partial payment of $400 is made
on June 25, then the amount owing on July 1 would be the interest on the amount
owing as of June 1 ($1,423.70) for 24 days (June 1 to 24 inclusive) plus
interest on $1,023.70 for 6 days (June 25 to 30 inclusive) plus the outstanding
principal amount of $1,022.64:<br /><ul class="noBullet fontSize85"><li class="noWrap"><p>(24 days <strong>[Divide by]</strong> 365) <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 8.45% <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> $1,423.70 = $7.91</p></li><li class="noWrap"><p>(6 days <strong>[Divide by]</strong> 365) <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> 8.45% <strong>[Multiply by]</strong> $1,023.70 = $1.42</p></li><li class="noWrap"><p>Outstanding principal amount  = $1,023.70</p></li><li class="noWrap"><p>Total owing as of July 1 = $1,033.03</p></li></ul><p>Note that the interest is compounded monthly and added to the total amount outstanding
once a month on the statement date.</p></li></ol></appendix></appendices></doc>