<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Security and Contracting Management Standard" documentID="12232" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PolicyInstrumentSchema.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="1. Introduction"><section anchor="1.1" title="1.1 Purpose and scope"><p>This document establishes the operational standard for implementing the Security policy in the contracting process. 
The standard contains both requirements, indicated by use of the word "must" in sentences appearing in italics, and 
recommended safeguards, indicated by use of the word "should."</p></section><section anchor="1.2" title="1.2 Roles and responsibilities"><p>Departments are responsible for protecting sensitive information and assets under their control according to the 
Security policy and its operational standards. This responsibility applies to all phases of the contracting process, 
including bidding, negotiating, awarding, performance and termination of contracts, as well as to internal government 
operations.</p><p>Whether a contract is within or outside a department's delegated contracting responsibilities, the department is 
responsible for identifying sensitive information and assets warranting safeguards.</p><p>The department has a choice for contracts that are within a department's delegated contracting responsibilities 
and that involve access to sensitive Canadian government information and assets. The department may itself ensure that 
the contractor meets the appropriate security requirements, or request that Public Works and Government Services Canada 
(PWGSC) perform this task. Departments should consider using the services of PWGSC when the security requirements are 
complex and require more than personnel screening. When the department chooses to use PWGSC's services, the two parties 
should prepare a written agreement on their respective responsibilities, to provide accountability.</p><p>For contracts that are outside a department's delegated contracting responsibilities and that involve access to 
sensitive information and assets, PWGSC is responsible for ensuring compliance with the appropriate security requirements. 
In this regard, PWGSC is responsible for assessing threats and risks and for consulting with the department on risk 
management decisions that may involve either extraordinary risk or expense.</p><p>Where a department is the contracting authority, it is responsible for arranging RCMP reviews of information technology 
security, as required. Otherwise, Public Works and Government Services Canada arranges these reviews.</p></section><section anchor="1.3" title="1.3 Guidance"><p>Enquiries about this standard should be directed to the responsible officers in departmental headquarters who, in 
turn, may seek interpretations from the <a href="/cioscripts/cu-cn/contact-eng.asp?who=/sim-gsi/">Security and Identity Management Division</a>.</p><p>Public Works and Government Services Canada provides advice and guidance to departments, contractors and potential 
contractors on the security requirements of contracts that require access to sensitive information and assets. This 
includes contracts for goods, services, construction, building services and leases. PWGSC may be contacted at the following 
address:</p><address>Industrial and Corporate Security Directorate<br />
Public Works and Government Services Canada<br />
Place du Portage, 10B3, Phase III<br />
Ottawa, Ontario<br />
K1A 0S5</address></section></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="2. Security and contracting management"><section anchor="2.1" title="2.1 General"><p>Each administrative step involved in developing and managing a contract might have implications for identifying 
of security requirements. Therefore, departmental security and contract administration policies and procedures should 
be cross referenced.</p><p>When a department is responsible for contracting security, it must check the status of the contractor with PWGSC 
and inform PWGSC when the department has determined that the contractor meets the appropriate security requirements. 
The decision that a contractor meets appropriate security requirements must be documented.</p><p>There may be special circumstances, determined by a threat and risk assessment (TRA) for contracts involving access 
to designated information and assets, where the step of ensuring that a contractor complies with security requirements 
before it is granted access may be replaced by a contractual clause. Such a clause should stipulate that security requirements 
must be met within six months of the contract being awarded. For contracts of less than six months, the clause should 
stipulate that the security requirements must be met before half the contract period has elapsed. Access may not be 
granted until the security requirements are met.</p><p>Departmental policies and procedures should specify the conditions for such exceptions, including approval of a 
TRA by the responsible manager and consultation with departmental security officials.</p><p>Departmental policies and procedures should also provide for scheduled and unscheduled work site inspections, and 
for the safeguarding of sensitive waste until it is destroyed by an approved method.</p></section><section anchor="2.2" title="2.2 Security requirements checklist"><p>Departments must use the Security Requirements Checklist to define the security requirements for contracts for which 
PWGSC is the contracting authority. This requirement also applies to call-ups against standing offers, when the standing 
offer or call-up, or both, contains security requirements.</p><p>The completed Security Requirements Checklist (SRCL) should accompany all requisitions and related contractual documents, 
including subcontracts, that contain security requirements. It does not replace the necessary clauses in the contract 
that specify security requirements. PWGSC has developed standard security clauses for use in contracts having different 
requirements.</p><p>The SRCL should as well be completed when a department retains contracting authority.</p><p>The SRCL can be purchased from PWGSC through departmental purchasing sections or through PWGSC Customer Service.</p></section><section anchor="2.3" title="2.3 International industrial security contracts"><p>As the government contracting authority, PWGSC is responsible for ensuring compliance with international industrial 
security agreements, arrangements and memoranda of understanding.</p><p>Therefore, departments must process through PWGSC:</p><ul><li>Contracts that afford access to sensitive foreign government information and assets.</li><li>Contracts that afford foreign contractors access to sensitive Canadian government information and assets.</li><li>Contracts that afford foreign or Canadian contractors access to sensitive information and assets as defined 
	in the documents entitled Identifying INFOSEC and INFOSEC Release.</li></ul><p>See the Industrial Security Manual for information on industrial security.</p></section></chapter></chapters><appendices><appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A - References"><ul><li>Identifying INFOSEC (NITSM 9/91), Communications Security Establishment</li><li>Industrial Security Manual, Supply and Services Canada, 1992</li><li>INFOSEC Release (NITSM(D) 7/90), Communications Security Establishment</li><li>"Security Requirements Checklist", (TBS/SCT Form number 350-103, NATO Form number 7540-21-909-5042)</li><li>Standard Acquisition Clauses and Conditions Manual (SACC), Supply and Services Canada, 1991</li><li>Treasury Board Contracts directive, Appendix C, "Contracting" volume, Treasury Board Manual</li></ul></appendix></appendices></doc>