<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Operational Security Standard - Readiness Levels for Federal Government Facilities" documentID="12331" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PolicyInstrumentSchema.xsd"><notetoreader>Note: this is a condensed and unclassified version of this Readiness Level Standard. For specific 
detail, refer to the Official version.</notetoreader><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="1. Preamble"><p>National or international events may require the implementation of enhanced security readiness levels beyond the 
baseline levels set out in the Government Security Policy (GSP) and Occupational Health and Safety Policies. This standard 
sets out the various levels of heightened security that are to be applied within government facilities in Canada in 
times of increased threat. In accordance with Section 10.13 of the GSP dated February 2002, these provisions are meant 
to complement, not replace, any existing security measures departments and agencies (hereafter referred to as departments) 
have implemented to deal with increased threat situations. There will be a separate notification system for cyber alerts.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="2. Application"><p>This standard applies across the Government of Canada in whole or to specified departments.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="3" title="3. Declaration and Application of Security Readiness Levels"><p>Depending on circumstances, security readiness levels 1 and 2 generally apply to an entire department, or the Government 
of Canada as a whole. When deemed necessary, based on the type and level of threat, the application of additional safeguards 
identified within Levels 3 and 4 may apply to a particular department, facility, group of facilities, or a geographical 
area. When it is in the interests of national security, the Privy Council Office (PCO) shall direct departments, through 
their Departmental Security Officers (DSO's), to implement appropriate security readiness levels, along with appropriate 
communication strategies and other requirements.</p><p>The Office of Critical Infrastructure Protection and Emergency Preparedness (OCIPEP) has the mechanism in place 
to disseminate PCO decisions, specifying the requirement for DSOs to implement a higher readiness level. The Treasury 
Board Secretariat is responsible for co-ordinating security communications and for providing security advice and guidance 
to departments.</p><p>Departments based on a threat assessment may, on their own, activate higher security readiness levels; however, 
these must be reported to the Director PCO Security Operations without delay (613) 957-5363. Departments must establish 
a governance structure, identifying roles and responsibilities, levels of authority and reporting requirements for 
declaring higher security readiness levels. In some cases, depending on their size and location, the application of 
security measures will vary. Appropriate authorities shall also determine when to return to lower levels of readiness.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="4" title="4. Readiness Level Sensitivity and Security Classification"><p>Although this standard in its entirety is classified, for the purposes of information exchange, this unclassified 
version may be made available for widespread distribution. Specific actions and safeguards prescribed within each level 
will remain Confidential. For additional detail, please contact your respective Departmental Security Officer.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="5" title="5. Incident Reporting"><p>Suspected acts of terrorism must be reported immediately to the local police. The Departmental Security Officer 
must advise the RCMP National Operation Centre at 613-993-4460.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="6" title="6. Security Readiness Level 1"><p><strong><span class="underLine">DEFINITION</span>:</strong> Security Readiness Level 1 is baseline security and 
applies to the normal state of vigilance in most government facilities. In this situation, as a minimum, departments 
must:</p><ol class="lower-alpha"><li>ensure the safeguarding of personnel and assets by applying previously accepted baseline security requirements 
as stipulated within the Government Security Policy (GSP), combined with newly adopted standards, in the following 
areas:
<ul><li>Security Screening</li><li>Physical Security including:
	<ul><li>mandatory control of all access points within all federal facilities, including visitor control.</li><li>Screening for suspicious packages of incoming mail/deliveries.</li></ul></li><li>Information Technology Security</li><li>Business Continuity Planning</li><li>Security in Contracting</li><li>Security Awareness</li><li>Protection of Personnel</li></ul></li><li>identify essential personnel (as defined within their business continuity plans) in the eventuality that there 
is an immediate requirement to escalate to Readiness Level 3, (refer to Readiness Level 3 for specifics).</li><li>ensure that appropriate plans are in place to deal with emergency situations as stipulated by the GSP, Canada 
Labour Code and Occupational Health and Safety Policies.</li><li>departments are to designate a Communication Spokesperson for security matters.</li><li>notify employees who travel internationally to consult with the Department of Foreign Affairs and International 
Trade prior to departure at: <a href="http://www.voyage.gc.ca/" title="Foreign Affairs and International Trade Canada">www.voyage.gc.ca</a></li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="7" title="7. Security Readiness Level 2"><p><strong><span class="underLine">DEFINITION</span>:</strong> Security Readiness Level 2 applies when there is an 
increased threat to Government of Canada personnel, assets and delivery of critical services which warrants enhanced 
vigilance. Depending on the nature of the threat, the measures in this readiness level could be maintained for extended 
periods and entail the following activities:</p><p>Notify employees of alert status and instruct them to be more vigilant.</p><p>In leased or shared accommodation, notify landlords, property management and other tenants about the enhanced security 
measures.</p><p><strong><span class="underLine">NOTE</span>: For details contained within this level, contact your applicable Departmental 
Security Officer.</strong></p></chapter><chapter anchor="8" title="8. Application of Security Readiness Levels 3 and 4"><p>As specified within the Declaration and Application section above, departments based on a threat assessment may, 
on their own, activate higher security readiness levels. Depending on the situation however, and based on there being 
a higher perceived threat, PCO may direct specific departments to implement higher readiness levels to specific location(s).</p></chapter><chapter anchor="9" title="9. Security Readiness Level 3"><p><strong><span class="underLine">DEFINITION</span>:</strong> Security Readiness Level 3 applies when there is a higher 
and more predicable threat which therefore warrants heightened vigilance. The implementation of this level for more 
than a short period will affect service delivery. Normally, this level will be maintained for a specified period of 
time and apply to a particular department, facility, group of facilities, or a geographical area. It entails the following 
measures:</p><p>Notify employees of alert status and instruct them to be more vigilant.</p><p>In leased or shared accommodation, notify landlords, property management and other tenants about the enhanced security 
measures.</p><p><strong><span class="underLine">NOTE</span>: For details contained within this level, contact your applicable Departmental 
Security Officer.</strong></p></chapter><chapter anchor="10" title="10. Security Readiness Level 4"><p><strong><span class="underLine">DEFINITION</span>:</strong>Security Readiness Level 4 is the highest security level 
and applies in an immediate area where an attack has taken place or when intelligence has been received that action 
against a specific location or person is likely. This level will be maintained for very limited period of time at a 
specific location or group of locations. The following measures will be put in place:</p><p>Notify employees of alert status and instruct them to be more vigilant.</p><p>In leased or shared accommodation, notify landlords, property management and other tenants about the enhanced security 
measures.</p><p><strong><span class="underLine">NOTE</span>: For details contained within this level, contact your applicable Departmental 
Security Officer.</strong></p></chapter><chapter anchor="11" title="11. Enquiries"><p>For enquiries regarding this policy instrument, please contact the <a href="/cioscripts/cu-cn/contact-eng.asp?who=/sim-gsi/">Security and Identity Management Division</a>.</p></chapter></chapters></doc>